<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of Lewisham (but vulgarly miscalled Dulwich) wells in Kent shewing the time and manner of their discovery, the minerals with which they are impregnated, the several diseases experience hath found them good for, with directions for the use of them, &amp;c. / by John Peter, physician.</title>
            <author>Peter, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54498</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13465</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12254945</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12254945</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57358</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54498)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57358)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 157:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of Lewisham (but vulgarly miscalled Dulwich) wells in Kent shewing the time and manner of their discovery, the minerals with which they are impregnated, the several diseases experience hath found them good for, with directions for the use of them, &amp;c. / by John Peter, physician.</title>
                  <author>Peter, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 88 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. James for Sam. Tidmarsh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hydrotherapy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mineral waters --  England --  London.</term>
               <term>Lewisham (London, England)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57358:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF LEWISHAM (<hi>But Vulgarly Miſcalled</hi> DULWICH) WELLS IN KENT. SHEWING The Time and Manner of their <hi>Diſcovery,</hi> the <hi>Minerals</hi> with which they are <hi>Impregnated,</hi> the ſeveral <hi>Diſeaſes Experience</hi> hath found them good for; with <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections</hi> for the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN PETER</hi> Phyſician.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. James</hi> for <hi>Sam. Tidmarsh</hi> at the <hi>Kings-head</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57358:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57358:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>REVERENDISSIMO Celeberrimo, ex ſuis Virtutibus Ornatiſſimoque JOHANNI EPISCOPO ROFFENSI, DECANO WESTMONASTERIENSI, TOTIUS <hi>ANGLIAE</hi> Eleemoſinarchoque.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HOmines, inter tot ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantia, ſolos divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis animatos menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, in medium <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis Globum, ideo eſſe collo calos, mihi videtur, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendiſſime
<pb facs="tcp:57358:3"/>Praeſul, ut inde, ad omnia extremis Mundi terminis concluſa, oculos convertentes, variarum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turarum, quas ſingulae partes Mundi continent, diligenti perſcrutatione, Sapientiam &amp; Bonitatem Dei agnoſcerent, atque res ad rectè, beatéque vivendum utiles eligerent: Etenim nihil in rerum na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura adeò tenue eſt, aut ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectum, quod innatis viribus, inſitiſque à natura officiis careat, quae diligentius &amp; exactius introſpecta, non ſolum divinam humanarum rerum curam in bonorum
<pb facs="tcp:57358:3"/>animis confirmant, verum etiam ſua Praeſidia vitae ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferunt. Quid <hi>Aqua</hi> vilius, aut abjectius vulgò habetur? adeo enim communis, atque ubique in manus eſt, ut vel nolentes pedes lavet; nihilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ejus virtus cumque noſtris corporibus <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> â naturae ſtudioſis hominibus cognita, non mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimam in arte Medendi parrem peperit.</p>
            <p>Diverſarum Aquarum prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidio temperatura humorum aequabilis, vitaeque conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens in hominum corporibus
<pb facs="tcp:57358:4"/>conſervatur. Morbi verò a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troces (non tantum familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, ſed inſoliti in tenebris latentes) ita manifeſtè pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligantur, ut earum alias ad membra corporis fovenda, conſervandaque; alias verò ad certos morbos internos depellendos, divinitus orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, atque hominibus <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore praeſtituto</hi> Divinâ Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>videntiâ monſtratas eſſe, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat non credere. In talium numero haec eſt, cujus prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter egregias jam approbatas, inveſtigataſque virtutes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſim, perque tuam Dioeſeſin perbenè notas; atque id por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò
<pb facs="tcp:57358:4"/>propter plurimas adhuc latentes qualitites, diligenti obſervatione, fidelique pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batione fortè inveſtigandas, de illâ gratioſa Providentiae benevolentia optimè meruit; quae ſequentis impoliti Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatus materia eſt ſubjecta.</p>
            <p>Cujus Patrocinium ſuſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere (gratiori modo non poſito <hi>(Nil dat quod non habet)</hi> quo animi, non immemoris benevolorum tui favoris ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diorum, gratia manifeſta reddatur quae nec te, nec totum Mundum fugat) te (Candidiſſime Praeſul) ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicari
<pb facs="tcp:57358:5"/>quodammodo cogor: Dummodo verear, ne ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinis Charibdin vitare ſtudens, in audaciae Scyllam incidam: ſed non tam gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis tibi fortè videbor, quum in gratioſiſſimam tuam vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit mentem; hoc auſum Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis etiam ipſius Naturae eſſe aemulationem. Omnia <hi>Inferiora</hi> erga <hi>Superiora</hi> tam Officio, quam auxilii, favoriſque gratiâ, movent <hi>Corpora;</hi> Stellae minores eſſe <hi>Orientales</hi> aliter non poſſunt, niſi <hi>Solis</hi> Conjunctionem aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequuntur: Sed nil mihi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitatem ab audaciae &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verecundiae
<pb facs="tcp:57358:5"/>imputatione, niſi ex imia tua <hi>Comitas, affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitaſque</hi> (omnium amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem conciliantes) promit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere videtur: Sub hoc teg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine placidè recubans, non levis me ſpes tenet, quod non dedigneris accipere, &amp;, ut benevolentiſſimè cepiſti, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgere pergas: Hoc etiam huic <hi>Opellae</hi> ex hac <hi>Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catione</hi> promittere poſſum, eam gratiorem omnibus futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>tanti,</hi> &amp; <hi>talis</hi> Viri <hi>Nomen</hi> ſibi praeſcripſerit: &amp; ſi Quidpiam praeſtiterim, quale in affectationem alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non quadrat, de his non
<pb facs="tcp:57358:6"/>ita valde laboro; mihi ſatis eſt, ſi <hi>tibi</hi> uni, <hi>Sagaciſſime Praeſul,</hi> prober, &amp; ex hac <hi>Opella</hi> fuiſſe agnoſcar,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>E Muſaeolo meo</hi> Lewiſhamiae <date>
                     <hi>8. die</hi> Maii <hi>1680.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Tibi devinctiſſimus &amp; adſtrictiſſimus, tui obſervantiſſimus &amp; Studioſiſſimus <hi>Johannes Peter.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:57358:6"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THough the number of <hi>Books</hi> in moſt <hi>Sciences</hi> are in this Scribling Age unneceſſarily multiplied, amongſt which, alſo Treatiſes of <hi>Mineral Waters,</hi> as well as others, have had their part in this impertinent Superfluity: yet the ſole Conſideration that theſe WELLS were never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Subject of any Publick Tract, I preſume, will with the ingenious, acquit <hi>this</hi> of that Taxation.</p>
            <p>Various are the Cenſures which I expect, concerning this Undertaking (to which I have made my ſelf liable for the ſake of the Common Good) ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding
<pb facs="tcp:57358:7"/>themſelves through falſe Opticks, are ſo highly conccited of their own Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that though they light of it in their Diſh, ſtumble upon it in their way, yet they will ſtride quite over it, not vouchſafing it a look, as being of too low a rank to be able to ſupply their curious Noddles with fit furniture. I ſhall leave ſuch to be better tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tored by the Omniflorilegous Bee, who in her Chymical O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations deigns to make uſe as well of Natures home-ſpun Flowers, as of thoſe of the moſt curious Floriſts raiſing.</p>
            <p>Others vouchſafing, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, to give it the Reading, yet may look upon it as a preſumption in me to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the Task, ſince the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb facs="tcp:57358:7"/>Matter thereof is within the influence of our <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan Luminaries</hi> of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. I confeſs, it is a Task beſeeming ſuch eminent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of more profound Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and larger Experience; yet ſince the Eminent and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted Imployments (ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Merits of ſuch worthy Perſons) will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them vacancies for ſuch an Undertaking, their time being wholly taken up in the active part; I have adventured (after a fruitleſs expectation of ſeeing it done by ſome ſuch able Pen) on the enſuing Subject.</p>
            <p>Others I expect out of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and private Intereſt, to carp at this Brat for the Parents ſake; but for ſuch let
<pb facs="tcp:57358:8"/>them know, that I ſhould much undervalue my ſelf, if upon ſo poor and unmanly a ſcore I ſhould triffle away my time in anticipating their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections with a Reply. So that I ſhall with as much Contempt ſlight their <hi>Empty Noiſe</hi> in this caſe, as I have done the Perſonal Calumnies, they have been ſo <hi>wickedly-witty</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, and <hi>devoutly-zealous</hi> to whiſper about againſt me, in the credulous Ears of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded Patients. Nay, there is a <hi>Grenovillatical Fopp,</hi> that (taking the Opportunity of my coming, a meer ſtranger into <hi>Kent,</hi> not long before the laſt Plot was diſcovered) had the impudence magiſterially to give out (and that in company of ſome of my Neighbours at
<pb facs="tcp:57358:8"/>a Publick Houſe not far from my own Habitation) that I was a <hi>Papiſt.</hi> What ſhall I do in this caſe? What ſhall I retort? Shall I revile and calumniate him again? No: But there is <hi>large Scope</hi> and <hi>real Matter;</hi> No <hi>Matter</hi> for that, I am for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, I have learnt better things, my Religion hath taught me, <hi>That if I am reviled I ſhould not revile again.</hi> So that I will only ſay, <hi>A Fools Bolt is ſoon ſhot,</hi> which every unprejudiced perſon will eaſily conclude, when he underſtands how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable the Man is to judge of what Religion I am, by his being wholly unacquainted with me, and by being a meer ſtranger (as it appears) to all that can rationally pretend to know me; for I here declare
<pb facs="tcp:57358:9"/>he never had any Diſcourſe with me, tending direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or indirectly to any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Purpoſe, or ſcarce of any other Matter, and I am conſident, at that time (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he hath had ſince) he never had any Conference with any Perſon that was of any intimacy with me, or of Twelve Months ſtanding Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance. So that without Conjuration it is eaſie to tell that this Calumny muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily proceed from no other Source then the malicious Efflaviums of his Sick Brain: and therefore upon the ſame ground, he might as well have declared me to be a <hi>Turk</hi> as a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> only his Mother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wit was ready to prompt him that the laſt was the fitter
<pb facs="tcp:57358:9"/>
               <hi>Stigma,</hi> and (as Publick Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances then ſtood) might prove moſt ſerviceable for his opprobrious Deſign; whereas, if he had been ſo idlely buſie, as to pry into my Religious Circumſtances, he being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſmoak of many of their Chymnies, who have known me and my Communication all my Life time, might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, without any coſt, or much pains, have been ſatisfied that I am of the <hi>Religion</hi> (the fartheſt diſtant from Popery of any amongſt the Reformed) of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as it is now eſtabliſht; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by the gracious Diſpoſal of Gods Providence, had the happineſs to be Educated (for which God make me ever thankful) though I do not
<pb facs="tcp:57358:10"/>profeſs my ſelf otherwiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to my Education than to <hi>manuduce</hi> me into a <hi>Truth,</hi> which my <hi>riper Judgment</hi> (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on wholly deveſting it ſelf of that <hi>prepoſſeſſion</hi>) hath up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on free choice conſented to. To the confirmation of which (as far as the nature of the thing will bear) I could procure (if need were) a <hi>Teſtimonial</hi> from <hi>Perſons</hi> of ſuch <hi>Eminency, Religion,</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> that (if there was as much <hi>ſhame</hi> in <hi>him,</hi> as there was <hi>Cower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe</hi> in that Man at the Siege of <hi>Spoletto,</hi> whom Nature diſſavowing, degraded of his Breeches) would Analogically make his <hi>May-pole-ſize</hi> ſhrink into a <hi>Pigmy's Stature.</hi> But as for ſuch like Perſons as this, who eye more the <hi>Quis</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:57358:10"/>than the <hi>Quid,</hi> prejudicating the Work out of prejudice to the Author, they rather give a Badge of their own deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Weakneſs, than any the leaſt blemiſh to it; therefore I value not their Cenſure: As for the Judicious and Learned, I know they will judge like themſelves, of whom I had rather be deſervedly control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, than by the other igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly commended.</p>
            <p>Since we are all <hi>Debtors</hi> to <hi>Truth,</hi> the Candid Reader will not think it much, that I have <hi>Obiter</hi> ſpent a little time to ſet my Reputation to rights, thereby hoping ere long, to ſee my ſelf diſabuſed.</p>
            <p>The whole Deſign of this Tract is (contrary to thoſe Phyſicians, who (under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb facs="tcp:57358:11"/>that they were ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticious Characters) defaced the old Writing over <hi>Cicero</hi>'s Baths, which declared the names of thoſe Diſeaſes they Cured) to divulge to the World the manifold and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Vertues,</hi> which God out of his Goodneſs hath particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly beſtowed upon <hi>this Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; Bouum, quo communius, eo melius.</hi> That thoſe that never heard of theſe Wells, or at leaſt of their Vertues, might by this means receive infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and if, upon tryal, they reap any benefit, may be added to the number of thoſe that are particularly obliged to bleſs God for them.</p>
            <p>I cannot omit the taking notice of a very great abuſe
<pb facs="tcp:57358:11"/>occaſioned by a rabble of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners</hi> and others, weekly fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting theſe Wells on <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days,</hi> where under pretence of drinking of the Waters, they ſpend that <hi>Holy Day</hi> in great Prophaneneſs; who after they have (for the moſt part of them) gorged themſelves with the Water, do drink upon it an exceſſive quantity of Brandy (that Bane of Engliſh Men) or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrong Liquors, thereby many of them becoming greatly prejudiced in their Health (to add to their Folly and Crime) have not been aſhamed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute their Indiſpoſition to this Water; whereas upon a <hi>Rational</hi> (omitting the <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi>) account, the ſucceſs in ſuch caſes cannot be expected otherwiſe. This excellent Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:57358:12"/>(like other choice Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies) is liable to be abuſed by its undue Adminiſtration, many (and thoſe of a ſoberer rank, than thoſe before ſpoken of) thinking thereby to cure themſelves, do not only much prejudice, but oftentimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy themſelves. For in curing Diſeaſes, if it were ſufficient to know Medicines and Forms of Receipts, the <hi>Tranſlator</hi> of the <hi>London Diſpenſatory,</hi> hath to the meaneſt Perſon made the Phyſicians Imployment uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; and an <hi>Apothecary</hi> were then moſt probable to make the beſt <hi>Phyſicians.</hi> being ſtockt with a number of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts communicated by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>Phyſicians.</hi> And in the uſe of all Medicinal Waters (as well as this) the <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:57358:12"/>Advice by conſequence would be needleſs; but there is far more Judgment and Skill requiſite to diſcover the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe (and other neceſſary Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, as Cauſe, Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, Temperature, Age, Sex, Cuſtom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) than the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and without ſuch Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, how abundant and frequent miſchief do we daily ſee done, even by applying Medicines of themſelves ſafe? So that as there is a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Adviſing with an Able and Learned <hi>Phyſician</hi> in all Caſes where Remedies are to be applied, ſo in particular about the Drinking of this Water; becauſe by manifold Advantages (reaped by his many years Study in Natural Philoſophy, his many hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb facs="tcp:57358:13"/>Diſcoveries in Nature, his Anatomical Knowledge of Mans Body, of its Actions, Uſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) he is able by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Signs, to diſcover the Cauſes and Nature of Mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and from thence to know how to apply proper Agents to the Patient.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57358:13"/>
            <head>OF <hi>LEWISHAM</hi> WELLS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> Of Water in general.</head>
               <p>SEeing that <hi>Water</hi> is the <hi>Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Subjecta,</hi> of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> it is a pardonable Digreſſion to ſpeak ſomewhat of it in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; as of its <hi>Creation, Nature,</hi> and various <hi>Effects.</hi> As to its <hi>Creation,</hi> it is generally referred to the firſt Verſe of <hi>Geneſis;</hi> which is a brief <hi>Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or a <hi>Compendious Mapp</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi> of the whole <hi>Globe</hi> of Matter thereof, from the Outmoſt <hi>Circumference</hi> to the inmoſt <hi>Center,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57358:14"/>created in the Beginning: And ſince we do not find, that any new <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was afterwards created, we may fairly conclude that the <hi>Waters</hi> were created in the <hi>Beginning</hi> alſo; to which truth the <hi>Original</hi> Word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (which is tranſlated the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) methinks gives us ſome light, which receiving its <hi>Derivation</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Fire, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Water, intimates to us the <hi>Subject Matter</hi> of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementary Heavens;</hi> (for as for the <hi>Super-aether,</hi> and all other Spiritual created Subſtances (being poſſibly too <hi>Sublime</hi> and <hi>Metaphyſical Notions</hi> for that <hi>Age</hi> to receive) it doth not appear that they were any ſcope of <hi>Moſes</hi> his Deſign there to treat of, but of the viſible Works of the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> only; which being obvious, and lying level to their <hi>Senſes,</hi> were the liklier to receive admittance into the conſideration of the beſotted and unbelieving <hi>World,</hi> and gradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally allure them into a belief of the <hi>Worlds Creation</hi> by the <hi>Almighty God.</hi>) Hither may be referred that of <hi>Rabbi
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57358:14"/>Bechai</hi> (as tranſlated by <hi>Buxtorf. in Lexic.</hi>) <hi>Accepit Deus Benedictus ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; aquam, &amp; permiſcuit iſta in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicem; &amp; ex illis facti ſunt Coeli, i.e.</hi> The bleſſed God took Fire and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and mixing them together made the Heavens: So that, if by the word (tranſlated) <hi>Heaven,</hi> we have found Fire and Water, the next word (in the Text) being the <hi>Earth,</hi> we have gained the <hi>time</hi> of the Creation of the Elements, <hi>Fire, Water,</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> anſwerable to the <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metick</hi> Principles of <hi>Sulphur, Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Salt.</hi> And further, that <hi>Water</hi> was ſignified by <hi>Moſes</hi> to be created in the <hi>Beginning,</hi> is evident by the words of the next <hi>Verſe,</hi> where <hi>Water</hi> is mentioned under the word <hi>Deep,</hi> without any intimation of any new Creation, but (as it were) taken for granted, that it was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Beginning; that the word Deep in Scripture Stile is often uſed for deep Waters, or Seas, is very obvious; as, only to inſtance in that one place of the Royal
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57358:15"/>Pſalmiſt, ſpeaking of the Creation of the Earth (<hi>Pſalm</hi> 104.6.) <hi>Thou covereſt it with the Deep as with a Garment.</hi> From whence it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that there was not one Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogeneous Maſs of Matter created in the Beginning, but one Body expreſly diſtinguiſht into ſeveral He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogeneous Members, which were diſtinct and ſeparate in their Scitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and not confounded together. It was as Natural for the Water to be every where about the Earth, as the Air to be every where about the Terraqueous Globe, the Aether to be about the Air, and the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per-Aether above all, which is ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly expreſſed by the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> (<hi>chap.</hi> 9.6.) <hi>It is he that hath builded his Stories in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens,</hi> &amp;c. From which Original Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of the Elements we may collect that their ſeveral Bodies of Matter were proportionable; the Matter of Earth moſt denſe, and therefore loweſt; the Matter of Water leſs denſe and therefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb facs="tcp:57358:15"/>the Earth; the Matter of Air more rare, and therefore above the Water; the Matter of Aether more rare and therefore above all other Elements, next to the Super-Aether, which is mo t rare, and ſo fitteſt for the Habitation of pure Spirits. Now the ſaid Elements (which were created in the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) were then endued with their proper Elementary Spirits, pure and unmixt, which receiving Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition by the Holy Spirit did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their proper Qualities gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually and ſucceſſively, <hi>à potentia in actum;</hi> whereupon the ſimple Qualities of Drineſs and Moiſture in the Earth and Water, did not actually exiſt till the third day, at which time, <hi>God call'd the Dry Land Earth, and the gathering toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Waters call'd he Seas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Element of Water is elegantly ſet out by <hi>Pliny, lib c Hoc E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementum caeteris omnibus imperat; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras devorant Aquae, flammas necant, ſcandunt in ſublime, &amp; caelum ſibi quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57358:16"/>vindicant,</hi> &amp;c. This Element challengeth a kind of rule over all the reſt; it devours the Earth, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhes Fire, it aſpires even unto Heaven, and doth, as it were, not only clime up thither it ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but it carries with it whole Sholes of Fiſhes, heaps of Stones, and divers other heavy Subſtances, which afterwards fall down again with it; thus far <hi>Pliny.</hi> This is ſo neceſſary an Element, that no living Creature can ſubſiſt without it. How wonderfully are all Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables enlivened, the Spirits of Animals refreſh'd with the vivifying Humidity, and Balſamick Vertue, wherewith it is impregnated by its Digeſtion in the Clouds? Hence it was perhaps, that <hi>Thales Mileſius,</hi> one of the ſeven Sages of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Empedocles,</hi> do both agree, that Water is the ſole Principle of all things; the <hi>Spagyrick</hi> Maſters go not quite ſo far, who affirm it to be the material Principle of all Concrete Bodies.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57358:16"/>
               <p>As to the manifold and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Vertues of Waters, which Authors of good Credit do relate, it would be an <hi>Herculean</hi> Labour to recite them all; I ſhall therefore only for the Readers Curioſity and Delight, recount the moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and unuſual of them, which for Methods ſake I ſhall ſpeak to in this order. (1.) Of the Coldneſs and Heat of ſome Waters (2.) Of their Taſte and Smell. (3.) Of their various Colours. (4.) Of their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Currents or Runnings. (5.) Of their change of Quantity and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. (6.) Of ſome other Things remarkable in Waters.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to the Firſt, In <hi>Corinth</hi> there is a Fountain of Water which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Colder than Snow; <hi>Ptol. Com. Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Pliny</hi> reports, that there is a certain Fountain iſſuing out of the Mountain <hi>Nonacris</hi> in <hi>Arcadia,</hi> that is of ſo cold a Quality, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pote cum profluens ipſa lapideſcat. i.e.</hi> That as it ſprings out it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into Stone. <hi>Lib.</hi> 31. <hi>c.</hi> 2.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57358:17"/>There alſo he tells us of certain Springs, call'd <hi>Poſidianae</hi> (near the City <hi>Baiae</hi> in <hi>Campania</hi>) whoſe Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are ſo hot, that they boil their Meat commonly therein. Near the Sea Banks of <hi>Cuba</hi> there is a River ſo large, that it is Navigable, and yet it is ſo hot, that one cannot endure to touch it, <hi>Martyr. Sum. Ind.</hi> And as <hi>Ramus</hi> relates (<hi>Tom.</hi> 3.) There is a Spring near the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Tapala,</hi> which runs ſo hot that one cannot paſs over it; here we ought not to omit our hot Baths at the <hi>Bath</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire;</hi> The hot Spring iſſuing out of St. <hi>Vincents</hi> Rock near <hi>Briſtol;</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Inſtances of this nature (which this our Iſle doth produce) might here be particularized, if it were neceſſary.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the Taſte and Smell of Waters there is great variety: <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> writes of a Well in <hi>Sicily,</hi> whoſe Water is ſo ſowr, that the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants commonly make uſe of it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Vinegar. The Waters of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57358:17"/>
                  <hi>Eleus</hi> and <hi>Chocops</hi> for Deliciouſneſs and Sweetneſs, were famous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Perſian</hi> Rings, and of them they much uſed to drink, <hi>Johnſt. Cl.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 3. The Water of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> is ſweeter than warm Milk; and ſo is <hi>Vinoſa,</hi> near to <hi>Paphlage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> where multitudes of Strangers come to drink of it; <hi>Johnſt. ibid.</hi> The ſmall Fountain <hi>Exampeus</hi> in <hi>Scythia</hi> is ſo bitter, that it taints the ſweet Streams of the River <hi>Hypanus,</hi> after it hath run ſweetly Forty miles, <hi>Ibid.</hi> In the bottom of the <hi>Adriatick</hi> Sea, which turns to <hi>Aquelia,</hi> there be Seven Fountains, and Six of them are very Salt, <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyb Hiſt.</hi> But of the Saltneſs of Fountains we need no further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance than our Salt Springs at the <hi>Witches</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire.</hi> The wonderous pleaſantneſs of the ſmell of <hi>Cabura,</hi> a Spring in <hi>Meſophtamia,</hi> hath occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the Fable of <hi>Juno's</hi> bathing her ſelf therein; <hi>Plinie lib.</hi> 31. <hi>c.</hi> 3. The hot Baths that are diſtant from <hi>Rhegium</hi> 26 miles, ſmell of ſo gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57358:18"/>a Bitumen, that they ſeem to be mingled with Camphire; <hi>Johnſt. Cl.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Where alſo he tells us of a Pit in <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> whoſe Water ſmells wondrous pleaſantly. In <hi>Hilderſham</hi> there be two Fountains, the one flowing out of Marble, ſmells like the ſtink of Rotten Eggs, the other from Brimſtone, ſmells like Gun-powder; <hi>Agric. de Nat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. As for Colours they are dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent in many Waters. At <hi>Tungri</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> there is a Fountain, whoſe Water, when well heated, turns of a very red Colour, <hi>Pliny ibid. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubius,</hi> where it divides <hi>Noricum</hi> and <hi>Windelicia</hi> from <hi>Germany,</hi> its Water is as white as Milk and Water mixt together equally, <hi>Agric. ibid.</hi> The Water of the <hi>Maine,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where it paſſeth the Franks, and is fallen into the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> are of a Yellowiſh Colour, <hi>Johnſt. ibid.</hi> In <hi>Aethiopia</hi> there are Red Waters, and in <hi>Peru</hi> as Red as Blood. At <hi>Neuſola,</hi> in a Mountain in <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathus</hi> (an Iſland between <hi>Rhodes</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57358:18"/>and <hi>Candia</hi>) runs out of an old Paſſage under Ground, Water, that is as green as Graſs. At <hi>Ilza,</hi> the Water that comes out of the Mountains of <hi>Bohemia</hi> is Black; ſo is <hi>Allera</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> and there be Waters in <hi>New Spain,</hi> that are cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditably reported to be as black as Ink.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The divers Runnings of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter are wonderful: <hi>Strabo</hi> ſaith (<hi>lib.</hi> 12.) that <hi>Pyramus,</hi> a River of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> (which ariſeth from Fountains that break out in very plain Ground) that it preſently hides it ſelf in a very deep Cave, and runs many miles under Ground, and afterwards riſeth a Navigable River. Not far from <hi>Pompeopolis,</hi> in the Town <hi>Caricos,</hi> in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of a Cave of wonderful depth, a mighty River ariſeth with incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible force, and when it hath run with a great violence a ſhort way, it ſinks into the Earth again, <hi>Mela. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 6. The Water of <hi>Martia,</hi> after it hath run a long tract from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57358:19"/>the utmoſt Mountains of <hi>Peligni,</hi> paſſing through <hi>Martius,</hi> and the Lake <hi>Fucinus,</hi> it diſembogues it ſelf into a Cave, then it opens it ſelf again in <hi>Tiburtina,</hi> and is brought Nine miles upon Arches into <hi>Rome, Pl. lib.</hi> 31. <hi>c.</hi> 3. The River <hi>Troclotes</hi> in <hi>Norway,</hi> makes ſuch a noiſe, when it runs, that it is heard 20 miles, <hi>Olans lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 28. <hi>Beca</hi> in <hi>Livonia</hi> runs forth of a Rock with ſuch a fall, that thereby it makes many Men Deaf, <hi>Ortel.</hi> in <hi>Livo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Waters have ſometimes chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Qualities, and altered their Quantities. There is a Fountain in the Iſland <hi>Tenedos,</hi> which always overflows from Three a Clock in the Afternoon till Six at Night, from the time <hi>Sol</hi> enters <hi>Cancer</hi> to his Entrance into <hi>Capricorn,</hi> and all the reſt of the time it cannot be perceived to run at all. There is another at <hi>Dodon</hi> which always ſtops its courſe at Noon. <hi>Topha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> a Fountain of <hi>Anagnia</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57358:19"/>is dry, when the Lake <hi>Fucinus</hi> is frozen, and at other times it runs with great quantity of Water, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gric. ibid.</hi> The Waters of the Lake of <hi>Babylon,</hi> turn Red in Summer. <hi>Boryſthenes,</hi> a River in <hi>Scythia,</hi> at ſome times of the Year ſeems to be died with Verdigreaſe. The Waters of the River <hi>Caria,</hi> near <hi>Neptune</hi>'s Temple, were formerly ſweet, and are now ſalt. In <hi>Thrace,</hi> when <hi>Georgius Deſpota</hi> ruled, a ſweet Fountain grew to be intolerable bitter; and whole Rivers were changed in <hi>Boeotia,</hi> about the Hill <hi>Cytheron,</hi> as <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> writes. In the Province of <hi>Cyrene</hi> in <hi>Lybia,</hi> there is a Fountain call'd <hi>Fons Solis,</hi> which is very hot at Midnight, and as the Sun mounts up in the aſcending part of Heaven, it grows gradually cooler and cooler; but every day when <hi>Sol</hi> is got to his higheſt pitch of Altitude, it is frozen, and as he deſcends toward the Nocturnal Meridian, it by degrees becomes warmer and warmer, till
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57358:20"/>he is arrived to the Midnight Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and then it is (as I ſaid) very hot; ſo that the Water of this Fountain is always frozen at Noon, and very hot at Midnight, and every day as it grows cold, it grows ſweet; and as it grows hot, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes bitter, <hi>Johnſt. ibid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. There are no greater Miracles (ſaith <hi>Pliny</hi>) in any part of Nature, than in <hi>Waters:</hi> therefore, if I ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance to a ſtep higher, and raiſe your admiration to an higher pitch than I have done yet, think me not Hyperbolical. The ſaid Author relates, that in <hi>Hetruria</hi> the Water makes the Oxen White that drink of it, and that <hi>Cephiſſus</hi> and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leacmon,</hi> a Fountain in <hi>Macedonia;</hi> have the ſame effects upon Sheep; and on the other ſide, that <hi>Pemus</hi> and the River <hi>Melas</hi> make them Black. He alſo tells us, that the River <hi>Aleos</hi> makes Men Hairy that drink of it. The River <hi>Nus</hi> in <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia</hi> (as <hi>Marcus Varro</hi> relates) makes Men Quick-witted; and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57358:20"/>
                  <hi>Pliny</hi> tells us of a Spring in the Iſle <hi>Cea,</hi> which makes them Blockiſh. <hi>Ovid</hi> ſays of <hi>Lynceſtus,</hi> a River in <hi>Macedonia</hi> (<hi>Mel. lib.</hi> 5.)</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quem quicun que parùm moderato gut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture traxit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Haud aliter titubat, quàm ſi mera vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na bibiſſet:</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>He that takes of it but a moderate draught,</l>
                  <l>Trips, even like him, that with New Wine is caught.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And of <hi>Clitorius,</hi> a Fountain in <hi>Arcadia,</hi> he alſo aſſerts,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Clitorio quicunque ſitim de fonte levârit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vina fugit, gaudetque meris abſtemius amnis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Who of <hi>Clitorius</hi> drinks, will Wine diſguſt,</l>
                  <l>And only will after meer Water thirſt.</l>
               </q>
               <p>There be two Fountains in the Fortunate Iſlands, they that drink
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57358:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57358:21"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57358:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57358:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57358:23"/>of one of them will laugh till they die, and can have no Remedy, unleſs they drink of the other. The Fountain <hi>Zama</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> cauſes excellent Voices. At <hi>Bonitta,</hi> an Iſle not far from <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> there is a Fountain, that ſprings out on the very top of a Mountain, which makes Men Young again, cauſes Aged Men to be Juvenile, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calls their Youthly Vigour; (to teſtifie the truth of which (ſays <hi>Cardan</hi>) we have not only common fame, but the teſtimony of <hi>Peter Martyr Angerius</hi> of <hi>Millane,</hi> a Privy Counſellour to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> in his Decades of the <hi>New World.</hi> The Lake <hi>Argentinum</hi> in <hi>Sicily,</hi> will bear thoſe things that will not ſwim on common Waters. And in the Lake <hi>Aſphaltites,</hi> a Man bound Hand and Foot and caſt therein cannot ſink. On the other ſide, there is one in <hi>Aethiopia,</hi> whoſe Water is ſo thin, that it will not bear the Leaves that fall from the Trees. Such like Water there is at a place
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57358:23"/>call'd <hi>Cabalus,</hi> between <hi>Padua</hi> and <hi>Vincentia,</hi> which is ſo rare and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuions, that whatſoever is put into it, appears at the bottom in the ſame bulk and figure, as if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Air interpoſed. And the River <hi>Sylas</hi> in <hi>India,</hi> is of ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable rarity, that it will not bear a Ship upon it. In which Rank is <hi>Boriſthenes,</hi> which when it meets with the River <hi>Hypanus,</hi> its Water ſwims above it for many miles to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>Fromond. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 3. There is a Lake in <hi>Ireland,</hi> in which if you ſtick a Staff or Pole, that part which is in the Mud in few moneths time will be turned into Iron, and that part which is in the Water into a Whetſtone. There be not a few Fountains, Lakes, and Brooks in <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> that will convert divers Things into Stone, whereof ſome in a ſhort time, and ſome in a longer. In the Iſland <hi>Summatra,</hi> out of the Hill <hi>Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lvanus</hi> there ſprings two ſtrange Fountains,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57358:24"/>whereof the one runs pure <hi>Balſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum,</hi> and the other the beſt Oyl, <hi>Heylyns Microcoſ. p.</hi> 689. In <hi>Caria</hi> (in <hi>Aſia Minor</hi>) there is a Fountain called <hi>Salmacis,</hi> which inclines Men very much to Venery that drink of it, or bathe in it, <hi>Pompeius Feſt.</hi> I have heard it reported by credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Perſons in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that in the Province of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lceſter,</hi> there is a Fountain, in which whoſoever ſhall two or three times waſh himſelf, ſhall never become gray.</p>
               <p>Now though I have taken the pains to collect thoſe different Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and various effects of <hi>Waters</hi> (to ſhew how capable they are of receiving diverſity of Qualifications from the Earth) yet poſſibly they may appear to ſome as improba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and as much paſt belief, as the moſt ridiculous Relations in <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deveile.</hi> Wherefore to diſabuſe the Judgments of ſuch, I ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to diſcuſs their ſeeming im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities, and make ſome of thoſe inſtances, which ſeem moſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57358:24"/>Anomalous to Nature, to lie level to Natures Rule and their Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings, and ſhall leave the reſt for the Reader to ſalve, as a Whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone to actuate his Intellectuals.</p>
               <p>As to thoſe Waters which <hi>Pliny, Varro,</hi> and other Authors do relate to change the Colour of thoſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimals that drink of them; What impoſſibility is in it? What hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders but that the Qualities of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters transfuſed through their Bodies, ſhould do as much in them, as the ſolicitous care of one Night, or ſome ſudden ſurprize of the Mind ſhould with us? <hi>Camerarius</hi> relates of a Noble Youth, who having Raviſht a Maid, and being to die for it, he ſo deeply reſented it, that his Vital Heat and Spirits were ſo much extinguiſhed, that all his Beauty vaniſht, and the Roots of his Hair growing dry for want of Moiſture, it turned Gray, <hi>Mem. Med. C.</hi> 2. <hi>M.</hi> 15. The ſame thing happened (ſaith <hi>Scaliger Exer.</hi> 212.) to <hi>Franciſcus Gonzaga,</hi> when he
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57358:25"/>was impriſoned for a Traytor.</p>
               <p>As to the River <hi>Nus,</hi> which makes a ready Wit; and that Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that cauſeth Blockiſhneſs, doth not common Experience teach us, that Wine doth the ſame things? Which, if moderately taken, its Spirits are exalted into the Brain, by the Heat of our Bowels, where it quickens its Motion, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces a certain Gayety, which raiſes our Fancies, and gives us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Thoughts. But on the other ſide, when it is drunk in Exceſs, the Spiritual part ariſing in too great abundance, doth circulate in the Brain with ſuch celerity, that then Objects do appear double, and the Walls of places ſeem to turn round; and we are prone to Sleep alſo, which is occaſioned by the <hi>Pituita,</hi> which being attenuated by the Spirits of the Wine, glides into the ſmall Meanders of the Brain, and there condenſing doth hinder the Circulation of the Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Spirits: I ſay, What hinders
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57358:25"/>but that the like Effects may follow upon drinking of ſome Waters, which in their Subterranean Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages may imbibe ſuch like Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities from the diverſity of Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vapours?</p>
               <p>As to the Fountain <hi>Clytorius</hi> in <hi>Arcadia,</hi> which makes them that drink of it loath and abhor Wine, it may not improbably be imputed to a certain viſcous Quality in that Water, which ſticking to the Walls and Mouth of the Ventricle, may cauſe ſuch a Nauſeouſneſs.</p>
               <p>As to the intoxicating Quality of the River <hi>Lynceſtius</hi> (which <hi>Pliny</hi> calls <hi>Acidula,</hi> from a certain Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Acidity imparted to it) it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably receives its Quality from the fumoſity of Sulphur, which will eaſily affect the Brain by its Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cotick Vapours.</p>
               <p>As to that Fountain in the Iſle of <hi>Bonitta,</hi> which is creditably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to make Men Young agen, to cauſe the Winter of Old Age to put on the Verdure of the Spring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:57358:26"/>Youth: that I may not ſeem to impoſe impoſſibilities in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon the belief of the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous Reader, I declare my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus, It may by a Natural poſſibility, have a certain Phyſical Vertue, from certain Heterogene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous parts of which it conſiſts (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome by carring off the Sede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thoſe Humours, which ſuffocate the Natural Heat; and others aſſimulating their Balſamick Vertue to the Vital parts) which may wonderfully reſtore the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical Moiſture, and mightily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair the Humane Fabrick, though not in ſo high a manner, as the Juice of that Fruit of the Tree of Life in paradice; yet if I ſhould affirm that the Effects of them both were exerted from the ſame chain of Cauſes, only the later in a more exalted degree; I do not ſee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhould be eſteemed Hete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodox.</p>
               <p>As to the Fountain of the Sun in <hi>Lybia,</hi> which at Sun Riſing and Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57358:26"/>is Warm, at Noon Cold, and at Midnight Hot, Dr. <hi>Fulke</hi> ſaith, it may be by the ſame reaſon that Well-Water is colder in Summer than in Winter.</p>
               <p>As to the Lake in <hi>Paleſtine</hi> (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Aſphaltites</hi>) into which a Man bound Hand and Foot and caſt therein cannot ſink, it is by reaſon of its Saltneſs (upon which account it is called in H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Writ the <hi>Salt Sea,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>;) for common Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teacheth, that the Salter any Waters are, the heavier Burthen they will bear. Our Boyling of Brine till Eggs ſwim thereon, is a confirmation.</p>
               <p>Before I put an end to this <hi>Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the curious and inquiſitive Reader will not think it imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, if I ſpend a little time in anſwer to thoſe, that may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, <hi>What Water is beſt and wholeſomest for common uſe?</hi> To which <hi>Pliny</hi> briefly and elegantly anſwering, ſaves me a labour, <hi>viz.</hi> That which is moſt like to Air,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57358:27"/>and then it muſt have the qualities of thin, light, cold, moiſt, taſtleſs, ſmelleſs, and having its proper Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour: Rain-water by <hi>Galen</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for its lightneſs, is preferred before others, eſpecially that which falls in a Thunder-ſhowr; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not clear, and by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Exhalations wrapt up together with the Vapours, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give it my Suffrage. So Hail and Snow-water for the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cannot be wholeſome, to which agrees the Opinion of <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates, Ariſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Pliny.</hi> Some commend Ice-water, affirming it muſt needs be wholeſome and pure, it being coagulated of the top and lighteſt of the Water, the terreſtial and faeculent part ſubſiding at the bottom: But to this I cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, but muſt condemn it upon the account that Exhalations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually falling down from the Air upon the Earth and Water, do light upon the Superficies of the Water, and mix themſelves with it,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:57358:27"/>and by conſequence muſt needs be groſs and impure. The <hi>Rarity</hi> and <hi>Tenuity</hi> of Water (ſaith <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi>) is known by its waxing ſoon cold and ſoon hot, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Fleſh, Peaſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are quickly boiled, for that there is therein a difference in Waters, every good Houſe-wife knows. The worſt Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of all is <hi>ſtanding Water,</hi> as <hi>Lakes, Pools,</hi> &amp;c. But certainly <hi>Fountain</hi> and <hi>River Water</hi> are the whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeſt; eſpecially the laſt, being percolated or ſtrained through Sandy Earth, and partaking of no other quality; whoſe Streams be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rapid, and running with a ſwift Current upon an hard gravelly bottom, are often broke off by many crooked turnings and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: therefore <hi>Avicenna</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends thoſe Cities and places that are ſo ſupplied. And <hi>Plato</hi> (in his Book <hi>De Legibus</hi>) <hi>Prohibites his Citizens to lodge in that City where there is no Laws, nor any River-Water, by that (ſays he) his manners will be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57358:28"/>corrupted, and by this he will be in danger of loſing his health.</hi> For it is certain, that the wholeſomneſs and unwholeſomeneſs of Places doth much depend upon the Water they are ſupplied with, as might be here made good by many particular Inſtances. And I leave it to the <hi>Enquiery</hi> of the diligent <hi>Obſerver,</hi> Whether upon ſtrict Examination it will not be found that thoſe <hi>Towns</hi> or Places of Habitation, which are ſupplied with ſuch <hi>River-water,</hi> are not generally far more healthful than others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57358:28"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Of the Original of Fountains.</head>
               <p>HOw Springs or Fountains, are perpetually ſupplied with Waters, hath puzzled many Learned Philoſophers, both of Ancient and Modern Times. <hi>Aristotle</hi> thought they ſprang from Vapours in the Air, ſhut up in the Earth, and condenſed by Cold. <hi>Seneca</hi> conceited that the Earth was tranſmuted into Water; others that they come of Rain. But to enumerate the ſeveral <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores</hi> of the ſeveral Opinions, and to re-count their Reaſons, would be here in vain and ineffectual, ſince we have here a more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Guid to follow, a ſurer word of Propheſie, <hi>viz.</hi> The H. Scripture,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:57358:29"/>where we find the doubt elegant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cleared by the infallible Pen of the Preacher; <hi>Eecl.</hi> 1. 7. <hi>All the Rivers run into the Sea, and the Sea is not full, unto the place from whence the Rivers come, thither they return again.</hi> Rivers (which are nothing elſe but <hi>Fontium Concurſus,</hi> a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of Springs) <hi>Do all</hi> (ſays <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) <hi>run into the Sea and the Sea is not full; how comes that to paſs?</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as Rivers run into the Sea, ſo doth the Sea empty it ſelf by Subterranean Paſſages into Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, which by their never failing Streams do conſtantly ſupply the Rivers, which diſembogue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Sea again: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it ſeems, as if to Nature at the firſt there had been aſſigned a certain <hi>bulk</hi> of Water, perpetually to perform a <hi>Circulation</hi> in the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crocoſme,</hi> Analogical to the Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Blood</hi> and Humours in the <hi>Microcoſme.</hi> And I have often thought it ſomewhat ſtrange, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57358:29"/>amongſt all the Learned and Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Worthies (who have imployed themſelves to give an account of the manifold <hi>Reſemblances</hi> and <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies</hi> between the greater and the leſſer <hi>World</hi>) none ſhould hit upon the <hi>Application</hi> of the before-ſaid <hi>Solamons Circulation</hi> to the <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſme,</hi> till our famous Doct. <hi>Harvy:</hi> How obvious (one would think) had it been (to thoſe that had their thoughts buſied on that Subject) to apply the <hi>Veſſels</hi> containing the <hi>Blood</hi> to the Rivers above and under Ground? The <hi>Vaſa attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hentia &amp; deferentia,</hi> to the <hi>Subter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean Channels</hi> and <hi>Rivers</hi> above Ground; the former carrying the Water from the Sea, the later returning it thither again? How anſwerable, for largeneſs, are thoſe <hi>Veſſels</hi> which are near the <hi>Fountain</hi> of Blood in the Body, to the <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels</hi> near the Sea their <hi>Fountain.</hi> Again, How <hi>Analagous</hi> are the <hi>Branchings</hi> and various <hi>Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57358:30"/>of the <hi>Veſſels</hi> in our Bodies from ſeveral <hi>Trunks</hi> (ſubdivided again into <hi>Capillary Branches,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Humours</hi> for the Nouriſhment of the Solid Parts) to <hi>Rivers, Brooks, Rivolets,</hi> and thoſe other leſſer Conveyances (diſperſed both above and under Ground) for a ſupply to Nature for the generation of all Bodies. And what proportion doth the <hi>Pulſe</hi> hold to the <hi>Tyde</hi> of the Sea, the <hi>Syſtole</hi> to the <hi>Ebb,</hi> the <hi>Dyaſtole</hi> to the <hi>Flood,</hi> and the <hi>Periſtole</hi> to the ſpace between.</p>
               <p>And that there are <hi>Gulphs</hi> and <hi>Channels</hi> under Ground, by which the <hi>Sea-water</hi> is conveyed is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, when we conſider the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great <hi>Lakes</hi> that have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to vent themſelves. What way can the <hi>Caſpian Sea</hi> be ſuppoſed to be exonerated? For the huge Rivers, <hi>Volga, Jaxiares, Ochus,</hi> and many other diſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boguing themſelves therein, it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57358:30"/>muſt needs vent it ſelf ſome way or other. The <hi>Mediterranean Sea,</hi> into which the <hi>Ocean</hi> by the Straits of <hi>Gibralter,</hi> and the <hi>Fxunine Sea,</hi> by the <hi>Thracian Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphorus,</hi> with very many great Rives beſides do continually run, muſt needs alſo diſcharge it ſelf by <hi>Subterranean Gulphs.</hi> How comes it to paſs that ſome <hi>Lakes</hi> are full of <hi>Sea-Fiſh,</hi> and yet are of a great diſtance from the <hi>Sea?</hi> In <hi>Bainoa,</hi> a Province in <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> is a <hi>Lake</hi> of Salt Water, which hath above Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Rivers runing into it, yet it never increaſeth, and it is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with <hi>Sharkes,</hi> and many other <hi>Sea-fiſh.</hi> At <hi>Cajela</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> there is a Mountain towards the South, under which the Sea runs with a great noiſe. At <hi>Apamaea,</hi> a City in <hi>Phrygia,</hi> which is far diſtant from the Sea, many new <hi>Lakes, Fountains,</hi> and <hi>Rivers,</hi> brake forth about the time of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:57358:31"/>
                  <hi>Mithridatical War,</hi> one of which was <hi>Salt,</hi> and had an infinite plenty of <hi>Sea-Fiſh</hi> and <hi>Oyſters.</hi> Beſides we read of <hi>Channels</hi> and <hi>Rivers</hi> in divers Countries, which run a great way on the Earth, and then ingulph themſelves. In the Province of <hi>Cazcium</hi> in <hi>Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niela</hi> there is a great <hi>Cave</hi> in an hollow Rock, at the bottom of a very high Mountain, in which divers <hi>Rivers</hi> (after they have run near an hundred miles) paſs as into an <hi>Indraught.</hi> What can better ſalve the contrary Currents of one and the ſame Sea in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts, than <hi>Subterranean Channels,</hi> as of the <hi>Atlantick,</hi> &amp;c? Or what can give a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable account of <hi>Whirle-pools,</hi> in many of which there is ſuch rapid <hi>Circumgyrations,</hi> that if a Ship comes over them, they are in great danger of being ſwallowed up? Such an one <hi>Andreas Moralis</hi> (in his <hi>Dec.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 8.) tells us
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:57358:31"/>that he happened into, on the Coaſt of <hi>Hiſpanicla,</hi> where the Water was drawn into the <hi>Earth</hi> with that viclence, that with all the Toil and Skill he had, the Ship could ſcarce eſcape ſink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ink.</p>
               <p>Again, To theſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder-ground Caverns</hi> are referrable moſt of the many ſtrange and ſeeming unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable things, that have been found <hi>under Ground,</hi> eſpecially thoſe that have relation to the <hi>Sea,</hi> as <hi>Shells, Bones</hi> of <hi>Fiſhes, Masts, parrs of Ships,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telius</hi> tells us that at <hi>Berna</hi> in <hi>Swit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerland, Anno Dom.</hi> 46. in a <hi>Mine</hi> Fifty Fathom deep, a <hi>Ship</hi> was digged up, in which were Forty Eight Carcaſes of Men, and much Merchandize. And in <hi>Greenland,</hi> out of the <hi>Top</hi> of a Mountain, was a <hi>Maſt</hi> dug with a <hi>Pully</hi> hanging to it. Now a more fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable way for the bringing of theſe and ſuch like things to ſuch places,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57358:32"/>then by <hi>Subterranean Paſſages</hi> from the <hi>Sea,</hi> I do confeſs I am to ſeek. So that I hope by this time the <hi>neceſſary</hi> Suppoſition of <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Macrocoſmical Circulation,</hi> is ſufficiently made good, <hi>viz.</hi> That there be <hi>Subterranean Caverns</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Bowels of the <hi>Earth,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Sea-water</hi> doth make its <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciprocal</hi> Frisks and Meanders.</p>
               <p>Now though we are thus (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boveſaid) infallibly informed of the Original of Fountains (for though I muſt confeſs that it was not the deſign of the Holy Ghoſt in Scripture, to teach Natural Philoſophy, yet however, when <hi>obiter</hi> (or by the by) he is pleaſed plainly to drop any Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal truth, I hold my ſelf obliged to give my aſſent thereto) and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways priviledged before all other Opinions, in that it hath the moſt Ancient of Ethnick Philoſophers, as <hi>Plato, Thales,</hi> &amp;c. for its Abettors. I ſay, though it be granted that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:57358:32"/>from the Sea, through Subterranean Channels, yet there remains a knotty Queſtion, which hath proved too difficult for many ſearching Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophical Brain to unty, <hi>viz.</hi> How the Sea-water ſhould be conveyed to the very tops of Mountains; as that Fountain which <hi>Curtius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates (<hi>lib.</hi> 3.) that feeds the River <hi>Marſyas, Ex ſummo mortis cacumine excurrit,</hi> ſpringeth out on the very top of the Mountain; and as that Spring of freſh Water, which ſtreams out on the top of a Rock, which is in the main Sea near <hi>Scotland;</hi> and St. <hi>Winifreds</hi> Well in <hi>Wales,</hi> on the top of an high Hill, with innumerable other inſtances of the like nature. About the <hi>Dihoti,</hi> of which Philoſophers do not a little differ, <hi>Pliny</hi> aſcribing the reaſon of it to the Wind, which forces (ſays he) the Waters through the Caverns of the Earth. <hi>Scaliger</hi> to the weight of the Sea, which preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the Channels, forceth.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57358:33"/>the weight of the Sea, which preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing upon the Channels, forceth the Waters through the Earth's Meanders. Some refer it to the attractive Vertue of the Earth draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Moiſture to it like a Sponge, or a Fleece of Wooll. Others to the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea. And if the Poets Conceit may be admitted amongſt the variety of Opinions, he tells us, that</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Caerulea per ſtagna agitant liquentia Nymphae,</l>
                  <l>Alterius implent undantes roribus urnas,</l>
                  <l>Alteriuſque ſimul effundant, &amp;c.—</l>
               </q>
               <p>And I hope I ſhall not abuſe <hi>Jovianus</hi> his meaning, if I thus tranſlate,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>The Azure Nymphs i'th' Subterranean Deep,</l>
                  <l>Alternately their conſtant turns do keep;</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57358:33"/>
                  <l>To fill and empty their light Pitchers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — ſo</l>
                  <l>Fountains do never fail to overflow.</l>
               </q>
               <p>To which Conceit that of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus</hi> and his Followers, is not much unlike, who would have us believe that there be innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Spirits</hi> that inhabit within the Earth (as well as in the Air and Planets) having there their ſeveral Offices and Imployments, amongſt which there be ſome buſied about the Conveyance of <hi>Sea-water</hi> to the <hi>Tops</hi> of <hi>Hills</hi> and <hi>Mountains</hi> (within the Cavities of which they aſſign their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Reſidence) to whoſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement they alſo refer all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and viclent Motions, as <hi>Generation, Corruption, Chaſms,</hi> and <hi>Earth quakes.</hi> Now though we ought not to doubt of <hi>Gods</hi> Power by <hi>Spirits,</hi> which (being his <hi>Miniſters</hi>) can at <hi>his</hi> command effect this and many more Actions,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:57358:34"/>that be infinitely more difficut; yet to impute all things to them, which do not lie open and level with our Senſes, muſt needs be but a Sanctuary for Ignorance, and prove a mighty Impediment to all Ingenious and Philoſophical <hi>Diſquiſition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though amongſt the many <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena,</hi> there are here, or poſſibly may be produced of the Original of Fountains, it may be difficult to aſſure which is the true one. Yet if I ſhall propoſe one that can give an account of all Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, and is not contrary to what the Holy Scriptures do any where inſinuate, I think I have reaſon to be content, and the Reader will have no cauſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain.</p>
               <p>All Philoſophers do truly hold that the Earth and Water do make one Globe, which they demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate by the Moon's Eclipſe, which being cauſed by the ſaid Terra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queous
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:57358:34"/>Globe's interpoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and the Sun, and cauſing what is darkened on the Moon's Body to be round or globous, is an evident Argument, that it muſt needs be round and of a circular form it ſelf, of which thing the Holy Ghoſt in Holy Scripture hath not been wanting to inform us. There is but one Body of all the Waters, for every part of the Waters, as the many Seas, Lakes, Rivers, Brooks and Fountains, are joyned unto the whole, as Members of one Body. So that either above the Earth, or under the Earth, they are all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned together; as the wiſe King teſtifies in the before-recited place (<hi>Eccl.</hi> 1.7.) which thing the Royal Prophet elegantly deſcribes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.6.7. <hi>The Waters ſtood above the Mountains, at thy rebuke they fled; at the Voice of thy Thunder they haſted away</hi> (agreeable to the Almighty's. <hi>Ipſe dixit,</hi> at the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57358:35"/>
                  <hi>And God ſaid let the Waters be gathered together unto one place, and let the dry Land appear.</hi>) But whither did they fly? Whither did they haſte? Into what place were they gathered together? God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf reſolves us (<hi>Job.</hi> 38.10) <hi>I brake up for it my decreed place, and ſet Bars and Doors; and ſaid, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſhalt thou go and no farther, and here ſhall thy proud Waves be ſtayed.</hi> As if he ſhould ſay, I have by my word cauſed thoſe vaſt Channels to be cut in the Earth, thoſe great Banks, huge Rocks and Mountains to be caſt up to make way for the gathering together of the Waters, that I might, as it were, marry the Earth and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters together, that ſo they might be made one Globe, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Circle whereof I might ſit and view the Inhabitants thereof, as Graſhoppers,</hi> (<hi>Eſai.</hi> 40.22.) which thing (<hi>viz.</hi> That the Water helps to make up the Roundneſs of the Sublunary
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57358:35"/>World, is evident to ſenſe, as is proved by the familiar practice of Seamen, who when they go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to diſcover Land, ſend ſome body up to the Main Maſt, from whence he can diſcover it, when no body elſe in the Ship can.</p>
               <p>Thus far, I hope, we have by this time gained, that the Earth and the Water do make one Globe: And therefore as to that Queſtion ſo much bandied amongſt Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, Whether the Water be higher then the Earth? I thus reſolve. As, we find the Earth in its Superficies to be very much indented with Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Vallies, Hills and Plains; ſo is alſo the Surface of the Sea much unequal, occaſioned by the Motion which God in the beginning by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Aſſigned it; in which Motion the Maſs, or Body of Water, forms it ſelf round or Circular, according to its Natural Property: for the whole is like its parts, and every one knows, that a drop of Water
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:57358:36"/>let fall on a Table will form it ſelf round: So that it is not againſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to conceive, how the Sea in the roundneſs of its Figure may Mount as High, if not Higher, than any Mountain on land is High: nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Infallible Oracle, which aſſures us, that <hi>God gathereth the Waters of the Sea together as an heap</hi> (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.7) and that, <hi>he lifteth up the Waves thereof, they Mount up to the Heaven, they go down again to the Depths</hi> (<hi>Pſalm.</hi> 107, 25 26.) and why ſhould this Circular Mounting of the Sea be more Inconſiſtent with the Globous Conſtitution of this Terraqueous Globe, than the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains on Land, ſome whereof o re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>top the Clouds? nay, without thoſe Mountains of Water to Ballance (as it were) thoſe on the Land, it puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zles me to conceive, how there ſhould be made up a conſiſtent Regular Globe of the Earth, and Water.</p>
               <p>So that upon this rational Supoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the Sea (from whence all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:57358:36"/>Fountains are ſupplied) is as high, if not higher, than the higheſt Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain on Earth; it cannot rationally be denied, but that according to the Rules of Hydrology, it may by the Correſpondency of its level Force its Water through the various Conduits Veins, and twining Crannies in the Earths Bowels to the top of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Mountain, anſwerable to the Experiented Maxim; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na Aqua pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit alteram, er tantum ſurſſum elevat, quantum ipſa eſt elevata, i e.</hi> one Water preſſes another forward, and raiſeth it as high as its own Level is: For that it cannot be ascribed to the conceit of the learned <hi>Scaliger,</hi> who would have the weight of the bulk of the Sea-water-preſs the Water through the Earths Subterranean Channels, till it find away out, is Evidently proved by this familliar Example, lay an horn on the back, that both ends be equally and Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zontally high, and then fill it full with Water; now though there be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:57358:37"/>much more Water in the thicker end, than in the ſmaller, yet the greater Water cannot drive the leſſer up higher then it ſelf is ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated.</p>
               <p>There being ſome ſeeming Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to this Hypotheſis, which I fore-ſee may poſſibly ariſe in the Readers minde, it will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs here to anticipate and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer: As</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) How comes Fountain-Water to be freſh, when the Sea-Water (from whence Fountains are Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied) is Salt? I anſwer all Metals, and Minerals in the Earth, being produced of Salt, and the Earth it ſelf having its fatneſs, and fertility, from Salt, do greedily attract the Saltneſs out of the Sea-Water, as it paſſes through the Earths Bowels, for their Maintenance (even as our Fleſh draws its nouriſhment from the Blood in our Bodies) by which means being deprived of its Saltneſs it at length comes out pure and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57358:37"/>freſh at the Fountains mouth: and that the Earth naturally drawes Salt unto it, is proved by this Artificial Experiment, If you bind a piece of courſe Linnen Cloth over one end of a bottomleſs Cask, and fill the Cask with Earth, and pour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a quantity of Salt Water, and let it ſink through the Earth two or three times, the Water at laſt will come out freſh, the Earth ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drawn to its ſelf the Salt thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">(<hi>2ly.</hi>) It may be objected, Whereas we ſee that all Rivers run into the Sea, how can then the Sea be higher than the Land? I Anſwer, that onely proves the Sea lower than the Land near the Shore, where it is terminated by the dry and ſolid Body of the Earth; as we ſee in a drop of Water put upon a Table, where the edges and extremities of the Water, being terminated by the dry ſubſtance of the Table, are depreſſed, and lower
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:57358:38"/>than the middle, like an half Globe. For if a Meaſure was to be taken of the Terraqueous Globe, it muſt be taken from the tops of Mountains, and from the higheſt Sea, and not from the Vallies, nor the Sea-Coaſts.</p>
               <p n="4">(<hi>4ly.</hi>) If theſe ſhould fall into the hands of the Readers, ſo over Phyloſophical, that they would not admit of Scripture Teſtimonies (ſuch as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.8, 9. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.22.) for a ſufficient Anſwer to thoſe, that object, that if the Sea were high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then the Land, the whole Earth would conſequently be overwhelm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith. Let ſuch conſider, that the Natural place of Waters is above the Earth, as being a Body not ſo heavy as Earth; and being terminated by the dry Land, it there willingly receives a Check, and being Natureally Propenſe to a Globous Circulation, it flies back from the Shore, and betakes it ſelf for that end to its own Homoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:57358:38"/>Maſs, which according to its Natural Law may ſooner, and with more facility mount in the roundneſs of its Figure above the Clouds, than out-paſs its ſandy bounds.</p>
               <p>Though (as I have endeavoured to make out) all Springs or Fountains do receive their Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal from the Sea, whoſe Water by its ſecret Paſſages, and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Percolations through the Earth, is made freſh and clear, yet I would not be accounted ſo unphyloſophical, as not to admit of ſome ſecondary and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adjuvant Cauſes, ſuch as theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">(1.) Great Rains may be a Cauſe of the increaſe of their Currents; for 'tis obſervable, that in Rainy Weather there is a greater fluſh of Waters out of Springs, than in a dry time; nay, ſometimes ſome Springs are dry, and yield no Water, as in a long time of drought. And
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57358:39"/>theſe things happen by reaſon of the Harmony that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Air and the Earth; for when the Air is reſolved into Moiſture, the Earth and Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals are then affected (as may be ſeen on Stone-Walls, Glaſs-Windows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) and being moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened by the Air, they ſuck from the Sea-water in its Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean Paſſage nothing but Salt; but when the Air is a long time dry, the Earth and all the furniture of its Caverns (in the moſt ſecret Receſſes of which the Air will have admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) are ſo likewiſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thirſty, they eagerly ſuck in not only the Salt but the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alſo; whence it is that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Springs are dried up in long Droughts, but where there are great Veins of Water, the Water is diminiſht, but not quite dried up.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:57358:39"/>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2ly.</hi> Fountains may receive aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation from the Vapours of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean waters, which lighting in their paſſage upon Earth repleated with Mineral Seeds, and receiving actual heat from the fermentation of Minerals <hi>in ſoluris principiis,</hi> whilſt they are in generation; by the force of which heat, Vapours are raiſed up in the Caverns of the Earth, which fly upwards to the tops of Mountains (as water in diſtillation to the heads of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limbicks,) where being refrigerated by the air included within the Cavities of the invironing Rocks, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to the natural denſity of water; Firſt into drops, then after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Rain, they unite into one Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, and ſo by a longer paſſage col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting their forces, they break out into a full ſtream: Our Catarrhs, and Rheumes do bear herewith a great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogie, for they by the heat of our <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcera</hi> being evaporated into the head, and there condenſt by the coldneſs of the brain, do fall down into the body again in Rheumatick and gouty hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours:
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57358:40"/>Our Tears alſo do the like, Whereunto the <hi>Prophet Jeremy</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes; <hi>making our Heads as the Hills, and our Eyes, as the mouths of Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains:</hi> and the ſaltneſs thereof may be aſcribed to their ſhort Ambages from the Head to the Eyes, like as the ſalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome Springs, to their vicini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, their ſhort and ſtrait paſſage from the Sea. St. <hi>Clement</hi> hath a pretty Alluſion concerning Springs, (in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> (which <hi>Cyrill</hi> Patriark of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> preſented to our Royal Martyr, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, which was annext as Schedule, to a Manuſcript of the Bible, fairly writ in Parchment by <hi>Theca,</hi> a noble <hi>Egyptian</hi> Woman, about the year 320) p. 50. <hi>Edit. Oxon</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>i. e. The perpetual Fountains do hold forth their never failing Breaſts to ſuſtain the life of man, being made for his uſe, and health.</hi> Thereby, methinks, intimating, as if the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean Abyſs was (as) the <hi>Liver;</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:57358:40"/>the Subterranean heat, it's Native heat; the Vapours thence ariſing, the Blood; the Conduits through which it paſſes to the Fountain's Mouth, the <hi>Veines,</hi> which lead to the two <hi>Hills,</hi> the <hi>Breaſts.</hi> And as the <hi>Blood</hi> by the quality of the <hi>Breaſts</hi> is changed into <hi>Milk,</hi> ſo the Subterranean <hi>Vapours</hi> by the denſity they receive from their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Meanders through the Hills and Mountains, are converted into <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain-water.</hi> Whereupon,</p>
               <p n="3">(<hi>3ly.</hi>) Something alſo may be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Opinion of Air included in the Caverns of the Earth, which being condenſed by Cold, is converted into water; Though by no means it is to be allowed, as a principal Cauſe, by reaſon that the Air cannot rationally be ſuppoſed to undergo ſo quick and ſudden a Corruption, as is requiſite; neither can ſo many Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pours be any waies afforded for ſo vaſt and perpetual a ſupply of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet we may not on the other hand totally exclude it, but muſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it as an adjuvant cauſe, as may A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogically
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:57358:41"/>nalogically be collected from that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Cardan</hi> (<hi>lib. Variet.</hi> 8. c. 44.) where he tells us of a certain Sick man in <hi>Italy,</hi> who, in the year of our Lord 1481, did vent by Urine for 60 days together, 36 pounds of water every day; when as the Meat and Drink he dayly took exceeded not 7 pounds: So that the over-plus which he void<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Urine was 29 pounds a day, which in that ſpace of time amounted to 1740 pounds; and the weight of the mans whole Body was not quite 150 pounds. Now the Reaſon hereof is ſuppoſed to be the Air contained in his Arteries, which being converted into a watery ſubſtance, was emitted by the Urinary paſſages; and ſo being ejected, there was a ſucceſſive Supply of Air, and by conſequence of water.</p>
               <p>Though there be theſe, and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly many more ſecondary and acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal cauſes of the Supply of Fountains with water; yet the primary, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and never-failing cauſe is from the Sea, which being as high, if not higher, than the higheſt Mountain (as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:57358:41"/>is before intimated) eaſily and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally raiſeth its water through the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean Channels to the tops of the higheſt Hills, Rocks, or Mountains; which <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> is not a little ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the examples of many Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and Lakes on the tops of Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, which have ordinary ebb and flow with the Sea; as the Fountain <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopos</hi> in the Iſland <hi>Delos;</hi> which <hi>Pliny</hi> reports to keep its courſe with <hi>Nilus;</hi> alſo he mentions (<hi>lib.</hi> 2. c. 103) a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Iſle over the River <hi>Timavus,</hi> in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> which hath certain Fountains in it, which increaſe, and decreaſe, with the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea: which doubtleſs muſt have larger Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duits, than other ordinary Veins of water, that ſo they may uninterrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly keep touch with the Riſe and Fall of the Sea</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:57358:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>(SECT. III.)</hi> From whence it is, that Medicinal Waters do receive, their various Qualities, with the manner how.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>WAter</hi> is either <hi>Simple,</hi> or <hi>mixt;</hi> and ſeeing the ſimple quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the <hi>firſt,</hi> may ſerve as a Rule to diſcern, and judge the <hi>laſt</hi> by; it will not be amiſs towards the furtherance of our ſearch after contaminated Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, to define what ſimple water is.</p>
               <p>Simple water is thin, light, cold, moiſt, taſteleſs, ſmelleſs, and having its proper colour. Now where any of theſe Properties be wanting, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound; it is then mixt and ſtain'd by receiving and imbibing ſome other quality or ſubſtance, from ſome one, or more Subterranean Mines. <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith (<hi>lib.</hi> 31. c. 4.) <hi>Tales ſunt Aquae, qualis terra per quam fluunt.</hi> Waters do partake of the quality of the Earth they run through: But the manner
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57358:42"/>how they ſhould be impregnated with ſuch various properties hath been ſo hard to diſcover, that the Antients have wrote little of it, holding them to be ſacred and holy, as judging them to have their vertues immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from God, having poſſibly retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Notion from the fame of the River <hi>Jordan,</hi> or of the Pool of <hi>Betheſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> being indeed real Miracles, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in them a ſupernatural power. But we, (who acknowledge with St. <hi>Auſtin. Civit. Dei. lib.</hi> 7. c. 30) <hi>Sic Deus adminiſtrat omnia quae creavit, ut etiam ipſa proprios motus exercere &amp; agere ſinat, i. e.</hi> that God ſo orders all things which he hath created, that he leaves them to exerciſe their own Natural powers; I ſay, we, diſcard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Phanaticiſm in Philoſophy, ought to look out amongſt the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Nature for a Rational account.</p>
               <p>That all Medicinal Waters receive vertues from Subterranean Mines, is granted by all Modern Philoſophers, but the difference amongſt them lyes in the manner, how Minerals do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57358:43"/>their ſaid vertues to water; which thing, that we may the better and more methodically diſcuſs, we will in brief give a touch of the Generation of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals.</p>
               <p>As to their Creation, it is greatly probable, that they were created at the ſame time with the Plants, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there is no particular mention of it in <hi>Moſés:</hi> What fitter time for the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> of the Earth to be ſtockt with Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Seed, than when its outſide or ſuperficies was firſt furniſht with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable? and as (by <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.5.) vege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tables do not ſeem to be created per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſo neither is it probable, that Minerals were, but that their ſemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Spirits were ſo diſpoſed of in the Bowels of the Earth, that they might perpetuate themſelves in their ſeveral kinds. And that they are dayly ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated is confirmed by common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; our <hi>Tinners</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> filling up their Pits with Earth, after they had wrought out all they could, and within 30 years after ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſame again, have found more
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57358:43"/>Tin generated: the ſame is obſerved in our Lead-Mines in <hi>Darby-ſhire;</hi> and for many generations, it hath been ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in <hi>Ilva</hi> (an Iſland in the <hi>Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Sea) that Iron continually breeds as faſt, as they can work it out; nay, the Tools of Miners in no very long time have been oftentimes obſerved, to have been converted into the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of thoſe Mines, in which they have been left.</p>
               <p>In treating of the <hi>manner,</hi> how the divers ſorts of Minerals do impart their qualities to ſubterranean Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, we will, for Methods ſake, rank all Minerals under three heads: (1) <hi>Earths,</hi> under which we comprize Chalk, Ocre, Bole, Sulphur, Bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (2.) <hi>Concrete Juices,</hi> as Salt, Nitre, Alam, Vitriol, Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Arſnicks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (3.) <hi>Metals,</hi> as Gold, Silver, Iron, Copper, Tin, Lead <hi>&amp;c.</hi> how the firſt and ſecond ſort do it, it is not difficult to conceive. Thoſe <hi>Earths</hi> lying in the way where thoſe waters have their current, are waſhed away therewith, by which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:57358:44"/>means the waters become confuſed, and thick, and by reaſon of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral ſubſtances of thoſe Earths they carry along with them; after a little ſtanding, they will have either a ſetling at the bottom;
<q>
                     <l>Sulphurea Nar albus Aqua-—</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>It is the Sulphureus Water,</l>
                     <l>That doth make White the ſtreams of Nar.</l>
                  </q> as, Sulphur, Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or ſwim at top, as Bitumen. The <hi>Concrete Juices,</hi> as, Salt, Nitre, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they will either diſſolve and ſo mix themſelves corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally alſo with water, or elſe by their infuſion they will tinge the waters with a ſpiritual quality, and ſo Quick-Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Arſnick may doe; and not ſo on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but oftentimes, (like the following Menſtruums) bring along with them ſome tincture, or Spirit from other Minerals.</p>
               <p>As to Metals, various have been the <hi>Hypotheſes</hi> and endleſs the Diſputes of the Learned about the manner, how
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:57358:44"/>they communicate their qualities to water. But methinks, the readieſt way to Salve this, and all other diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of this nature, is to bring all to the Rule of experimental Philoſophy to deduce the cauſes of things from ſuch Originals, as (we obſerve) are producible by Art. Art is the Ape of Nature, and certainly the works of that muſt prove the reaſonable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries of this: And ſince he that is verſt in Spagyrical Experiments can prepare his <hi>Acetum Philoſophicum,</hi> his <hi>Elixir Subtilita is,</hi> and other ſuch like <hi>Menſtruums</hi> which by their pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrating vertues will diſſolve the hardeſt Metals, and be impregnated with their qualities; methinks, <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> her ſelf, which is the <hi>Art</hi> of God, ſhould do as much: <hi>Nature</hi> cannot be behind hand with <hi>Art,</hi> (which is but her <hi>off-ſp ring,</hi> and is beholden to her for what it hath) but muſt needs out do her by vertue of her many power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ferments, productive of ſuch po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Menſtruums, ſuch appropriate ſaline Liquors, as are able to reſerate
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57358:45"/>thoſe ſecret virtues which are lockt up in Metals, and ſet them ſo at liberty that they willingly unite and eaſily ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelves to be imbibed by thoſe ſtreams, that happen to glide that way: thus I conceive, by Menſtruums of Natures preparing within the womb of the Earth, are Metals reduced to a diſſolution, and by a fermentation of Nature, are made capable of impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their qualities to Waters. And thus alſo it's not difficult to conceive how the Waters of many Springs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come actually hot, and imbibe their ſeveral qualities, and how by their long ſubterranean paſſages, and many Meanders from the place of their Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibition, to the place of their erupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, their heat may be utterly loſt, and at laſt guſh out, as cold (as we ſay) as Rock-water.</p>
               <p>There is an Experiment of <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Rochas,</hi> which becauſe it clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrates theſe things, I will take the pains to tranſcribe, (out of Dr. <hi>French</hi>'s Art of Diſtil. <hi>lib.</hi> 5.) <q>As I was (ſaith he) with ſome of my
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57358:45"/>Companions wandring in <hi>Savoy,</hi> I found in the Valley of <hi>Luzerne</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Alpes</hi> a hot Spring; I began to conſider the cauſe of this heat, and whereas the vulgar opinion is, that the heat of Fountains is from Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains fired within, I ſaw reaſon to think the contrary, becauſe I ſaw Snow upon a Mountain from whence this hot Spring came, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melted, which could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly but have been diſſolved by the hot furnes of the Mountains, had they been fired; Whereupon being unſatisfied, I with my Companions and other Laboures (whom I could hardly perſwade to undertake ſuch a buſineſs, by reaſon they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid that fire would thereupon break forth out of the ground and conſume us) got Tools and ſet upon digging to find out the true cauſes of the heat of this Fountain. After we had digged 15 days (having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore perceived the water to be hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and hotter by degrees as we came nearer the Source) we came
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:57358:46"/>to the Original of the heat, where was a great ebullition: In three hours more we digged beyond this place of ebullition, and perceived the water to be cold, yet in the ſame continued Stream with the other, that was hot; upon this I began to wonder much at the reaſon of theſe things. Then I carried to my lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of this hot water (which was both ſaltiſh and acid) and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porated it, and of 40 Ounces I had in the bottom 5 Drams of ſaltiſh matter, which I then yet further purified, and extracted thence 3 Drams of pure Nitrous Hermetick Salt, the other two Drams being a ſlimy ſulphureous ſubſtance: Yet with this I was not ſatisfied, but with my Labourers went again to the place and digged 12 days more, and then we came to a water, which was inſipid, as ordinary fountain water, yet ſtill in a continued ſtream with the ſaltiſh and hot water: At this I wondred much, whereupon I digged up ſome of the Earth,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:57358:46"/>where the cold and Saltiſh ſtream runned, and carried it home with me, and out of an Hundred weight of it, I extracted a good quantity of Nitrous Salt, which was almoſt fluxile: When I extracted as much as I could, I layd the Earth aſide, and in 24 Hours time it was all covered over with Salt, which I extracted, and out of an hundred weight of this Earth, which I call <hi>Virgins Earth,</hi> I had four pound of this kind of Salt, which it contracted in the foreſaid 24 hours; and ſo it would do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly: Now this ſatisfied me in one doubt, for before I was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied, how there could be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſupply of that Salt, which made the water ſaltiſh, ſeeing there was but a little diſtance betwixt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipid water, and the hot water, and the conſtant ſtream of water waſht away the Salt, which was in that lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ſpace; For I perceived that this kind of Earth attracts this Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Salt of the world, partly from the air in the Cavities of the Earth,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:57358:47"/>and partly from the Vapours that conſtantly paſs through the Earth. After this, I took ſome of the Earth where the ebullition was, and carried it home and proved it, and I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it to be a Sulphur-Mine into which the former acid Saltiſh water penetrating cauſed an ebullition, as do Salt of <hi>Tartar,</hi> and Spirit of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, being mixt together, and as water poured on unſlaked lime. After this I began to queſtion, how it was that this Sulphur-Mine was not conſumed, ſeeing ſo much matter paſſeth from it dayly; but when I began to underſtand how all things in the Earth did aſſimilate to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves whatſoever was of any kind of affinity to them, as mines convert the Tools of Miners into their own ſubſtance in a little time, and ſuch like experiments of that nature, I was ſatisfied. And after all this I underſtood how this univerſal Salt of the world was to be had, and I could at any time mix it with water, and pour that water upon Sulphur,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57358:47"/>and ſo make an artificial hot Bath, as good as any Natural Bath what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</q> Thus far <hi>Mounſieur de Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which account it appears that that Earth, through which the inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid water run, did impregnate the ſaid water with an acid Nitrous Salt, which running through a Sulphurous Mine cauſed the ebullition; not far from whence the Spring making its e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, it iſſued out hot, but by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, if it had kept its ſubterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean paſſage much longer, before it had burſt out, it would have come out as cold, as ordinary Fountain wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and impregnated with its diverſe vertues from the before-mentioned cauſes.</p>
               <p>That we may underſtand the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt Mineral Springs, it is requiſite, that we conſider the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Minerals, that ſo we may or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly proceed, from the <hi>cauſe</hi> to the <hi>effect,</hi> or at leaſt may follow the <hi>Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects</hi> to their true <hi>Cauſes:</hi> and herein, following our former Method, we
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:57358:48"/>will begin with <hi>Earths,</hi> which if they be ſimple, are cold, dry, and aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent: if mixt with Niter; as, Fullers-Earth, Marle, &amp;c. they are abſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. All ſorts of <hi>Boles</hi> are Aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, and deſiccative. <hi>Turfes, Peat,</hi> &amp;c. are fat and unctuous. All <hi>Bitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina,</hi> as <hi>Amber, Terra Samos, Jet, Camphire, Coals, Rofin, Naphta,</hi> &amp;c. are hot and dry: but <hi>Sulphur,</hi> mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, and ſomewhat cooling.</p>
               <p n="2">(2ly) <hi>Concrete Juices</hi> are of diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent natures: <hi>Salt</hi> is aſtringent, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tergent, Purging, &amp;c. <hi>Niter, Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniac, Borax, Alum, Vitriol,</hi> are very Aſtringent and cold. <hi>Mercury</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Arſnicks</hi> are extream hot &amp; putrifying, and very venemous.</p>
               <p n="3">(3ly) <hi>Metals</hi> are of different quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: As for <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> upon what account the Antients ſo ſuperſtitiouſly overvalued them, I do not well know, but by reaſon they are ſo ſparingly bred in the earths bowes, I will alſo ſpare to ſpeak any more of them: <hi>Iron</hi> is Opening and Aſtringent: the open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quality lyes in the volatile Salt,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57358:48"/>as appears in <hi>Chalybeat</hi> wine; the Aſtringent in the <hi>Crocus,</hi> or Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtial part, as is evident by the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings thereof, after their Infuſion in wine, (the <hi>Volatile Salt</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from them) for then they are very Aſtringent, and ſtop all manner of Fluxes. <hi>Copper</hi> is temperate in heat, leſs Aſtringent, and more open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than <hi>Iron. Tin</hi> and <hi>Lead,</hi> are cold and dry: the former moving ſweat; <hi>Antimony,</hi> a kind of Metal; <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> ſayes, it cooles, bindes, and opens Obſtructions; and though neither <hi>he,</hi> nor <hi>Galen</hi> wrote any thing of its Purging quality, yet experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence tells us, that it purgeth violently both upwards, and downwards: And although the <hi>Antients</hi> tell us of no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that participates with it; yet that <hi>Argument</hi> is with me of as little force, as if it ſhould be denied, that it hath any purging quality, becauſe not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by thoſe Worthies in Phyſick. There be many more <hi>mixed Bodies, Flores,</hi> and <hi>Recrements</hi> of <hi>Metals,</hi> which are to be referred to the ſimple
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57358:49"/>
                  <hi>Bodies</hi> from whence they proceed, as <hi>Tutia, Minium, Ceruſſa,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Out of all theſe Subterranean Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances ſome Waters draw contrary faculties, and from hence it is that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes one and the ſame Medicinal Water cureth divers Diſeaſes, which are contrary one to another; which is occaſioned from the Heterogeneous partes, of which it conſiſts, ſome of them relieving, or blowing up the ſparks of Natural heat, whilſt others are reſtoring the Radical Juice with their Balſamick vertues; So that it is of <hi>this,</hi> as it is of <hi>Treacle</hi> and <hi>Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date,</hi> which conſiſt of a multitude of Simples of oppoſite natures, (hudled together, as it were by chance) which having received their due Fermentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and wrought one upon another, are made excellent for many Diſtempers: Or like, as it were, to the Chymical <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixir,</hi> or <hi>Panacaea</hi> (which though it is not eaſy to confute, yet very difficult to acquire its Proceſs, ſo as to bring it to perfection; if not as yet unattainable,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:57358:49"/>though <hi>Claudius Deodatus</hi> writes (<hi>Panth. Hygiaſt. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.) that <hi>Crollius</hi> to his great aſtoniſhment, and admiration, ſaw a man juſt at the point of death, labouring for life, with one only drop of that divine liquor in one nights time to be recovered to his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine and perfect health, and though ſuch a thing is mentioned by the moſt Antient Authours, as <hi>Meſue,</hi> who flouriſhed in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> long before <hi>Avi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen,</hi> and calls it <hi>Perfectum Magiſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um; Anaxagorus Clazomenus</hi> (who was before <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>) terms it <hi>Summa Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicina: Democritus</hi> hath a Copy of Greek verſes extant of that Subject; and our <hi>Roger Bashon</hi> calls it <hi>The Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xir</hi>) I ſay, the Reaſon, that ſome Medicinal Waters cure diverſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, which are contrary one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may bear ſome Analogy with the Reaſons, which the Spagyrick Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers bring for their Univerſal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:57358:50"/>
               <head>(SECT. <hi>IV.</hi>) Of <hi>Lewiſham</hi> Waters in particular, with the time and manner of their Diſcovery, the Minerals they conſiſt of; with a Catologue of Diſeaſes, they are approvedly found good for.</head>
               <p>NAture hath ſeem'd to ſingle out of all the Counties of Great <hi>Britain, Kent,</hi> and particularly to endue it with ſuch a fit Soil, and happy Clime, that it is productive of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of all ſorts of the fruits of the Earth, but even to a Miracle of <hi>Apples</hi> and <hi>Cherries,</hi> eſpecially the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> for which it hath been ſo peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly prepared by Nature, that <hi>Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> leſt ſhe ſhould (as I may ſo ſay) be tax't of neglect, or ill-houſewifry took care <hi>betimes,</hi> that it ſhould not lye idle, or un-improved: For as <hi>Pliny</hi> affirms, <hi>lib. — cap. — Ceraſi ante victoriam Mithridaticam L. Luculli
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:57358:50"/>non fuêre in</hi> Italia, <hi>ad urbis annum</hi> DCLXXX. <hi>is primum vexit è Ponto: Anniſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </hi> CXX. <hi>trans Oceanum in Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniamuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> pervenêre.</hi> So that Cherry Trees being brought from <hi>Rome,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Year of Our Lord 48 into <hi>England;</hi> It is greatly probable that they were put on Shore at their uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and much occupied Port <hi>Dubris</hi> (which we now call <hi>Dover</hi>) and ſo planted in this moſt proper Soil, as being the moſt <hi>Meridional</hi> Clime of any County of <hi>England;</hi> I ſay, as Nature hath bleſt the ſuperficial Soil of this County with a wonderful ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity for all ſorts of Fruits; So hath She not been behind hand in furniſhing its <hi>Womb</hi> with various <hi>Minerals</hi> proudu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive of not a few <hi>Medicinal Waters;</hi> amongſt which this water we are treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of, is very much beholden to God and Nature for its admirable Vertues. It is conveyed to us into ſeveral <hi>Wells</hi> contiguous together upon a <hi>Common Ground</hi> belonging to the <hi>Pariſh</hi> of <hi>Lewiſham</hi> (known by the name of <hi>Weſtwood Common,</hi> as lying Weſt from
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:57358:51"/>the Pariſh Church from which it is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant about 2 Miles) fed by Springs iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from an Aſcent, which the Golden Raies of the Sun ſalute at his firſt riſing all the year round. Theſe Wells are commonly, though improperly, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Dullwhieh Wells,</hi> but why <hi>Dullwhich</hi> ſhould ſo ſurreptitiouſly invade <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſham's</hi> Right, as to have this <hi>water</hi> called after her Name, and ſo unjuſtly to aſſume that honour to her ſelf, which ſhe well knows belongs to her <hi>Neighbour-Pariſh,</hi> I know no reaſon; for though through the ſimplicity of ſome, and the deſign of others, it hath generally for about 30 years went un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of <hi>Dullwhich-Water,</hi> that is, ever ſince the time of the firſt Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of its Medicinalneſs: Yet <hi>that</hi> (in this caſe) is too ſhort a ſpace of elap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed time to ground a <hi>Plea</hi> of <hi>Cuſtom</hi> upon. Now conſidering in what danger the beginnings of things (though we uſe our greateſt skill to prevent it) are of being ſwallowed up by Oblivion, and how irrecoverably gone, when a little o'regrown with
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57358:51"/>time; but eſpecially the reaſon of the firſt <hi>Names</hi> of things, which not being rightly and properly tranſmitted to poſterity, may cauſe various, and to us now unthought of, diſputes, and differences in the Ages to come: I ſay, theſe things conſiciered, we ought to be ſo charitable to <hi>poſterity</hi> as not to lead them into an errour. Beſides we ſhould even confront <hi>Providence</hi> it ſelf, if we ſhould not ſtamp the Name of the Pariſh upon theſe Wells, where the diſpoſing and digitating hand of <hi>Providence</hi> hath deſtined the eruption of thoſe Springs that ſupply them. The firſt terminating or ſetting out of the <hi>Bounds</hi> of <hi>Pariſhes,</hi> were not ſo void of Providential direction, or ſo caſual as ſome may opine. Upon which conſideration; I take it to be a Right due from every one to give <hi>theſe</hi> Waters their <hi>Proper</hi> Names. viz. <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſham Wells.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the time <hi>when,</hi> and manner how the vertue of this Water came to be found out and diſcovered: The more Intelligent of the Antient Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57358:52"/>do affirm, that they never heard of any peculiar quality it had, till about the year 1648, a famous <hi>Empirick</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> who being tired with the fruitleſs importunities of a poor Female Patient, whoſe habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was near this water, directed her thereto, as to a Remedy nearer home, whoſe effects by outward and inward application were ſo remarkably mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in her recovery, that thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they grew famous, and hath ever ſince become the ſubject of ſuch Empi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Experiments, as any would be pleaſed to make tryal of.</p>
               <p>The Diſtemper this Woman (whoſe fortune it was to be the firſt occaſion of the divulging the Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalneſs of this water) was afflicted with, was the <hi>Lues Venerea,</hi> or <hi>French Pox,</hi> (as it is generally reported) at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with malignant Symptomes, her Noſe being ulcerated, and her whole Body very much emaciated, from all which Symptoms by the uſe of this water ſhe was delivered in a few Months, by waſhing her Ulcers
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:57358:52"/>with it, and by dayly taking of it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly.</p>
               <p>But it is obſervable what the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Inhabitants thereabouts do inform us, <hi>viz.</hi> that in that very place, where now the <hi>Wells</hi> are, there uſed to be only guſhings of water conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trickling down, where multitudes of <hi>Pigeons</hi> uſed dayly to frequent, which place thereupon had gained (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the vulgar <hi>Swains</hi> thereabouts) the Name of <hi>Pigeons Quillet:</hi> which haunt of thoſe Creatures was enough to give intelligence to any obſerving and inquiſitive Naturaliſt, that there was ſomething more there, than ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ordinary <hi>water,</hi> ſomething where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the water was impregnated, that did invite, and delight <hi>them,</hi> ſome <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Aluminous Liquor,</hi> of which thoſe Fowls naturally love to be tippling.</p>
               <p>As God hath freely beſtowed his favours upon this water, ſo is it now diſpenſed <hi>gratis</hi> to any that deſire it, either to themſelves, or to any they ſhall ſend for it, every one being left at liberty to gratifie the Poor people
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:57358:53"/>that attend there dayly to cleanſe the Wells, that the water may be taken up freſh and pure) as they ſhall think fit, there being no cuſtomary uſage, or fixt gratuity apportioned: There is a credible but ſomewhat unaccountable report, that a little after the Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalneſs of this Water was (as above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) found out, that by the inſtigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a forward and active perſon (whoſe habitation by reaſon of its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinquity, was ſituated very advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly for the entertainment of any that would drink the water,) there was a Collection made of a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sum of Money, with a deſign to incloſe and monopolize the water, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence that the profit thereby accruing, ſhould be for the <hi>Poors</hi> uſe, and to that end a <hi>Well</hi> was dugg hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely wrought up with Brick and Stone, about which a convenient Plot of ground was deſign'd to be incloſed with a Brick-wall, and ſuch Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences added, as ſhould be afterwards thought requiſite. But it is poſitively affirmed by the moſt intelligent of the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:57358:53"/>Antient Pariſhioners, (who are the moſt faithful Regiſters of what was then done) that no ſooner was the Well finiſht, though ſupplied with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter very plentifully, but it loſt its taſte its <hi>odour</hi> and <hi>effects,</hi> which was ſo manifeſtly obſervable, that there upon there was immediately a final end put to that ſpecious Project: from which undeniable <hi>matter of fact,</hi> give me leave to draw this obſervation, that <hi>in behalf of the Poor (incapacitated to right themſelves) God oftentimes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſteps in for their aſſiſtance.</hi> Of the Truth of which Propoſition, the Royal Prophet aſſures us <hi>Pſ.</hi> 140.12. <hi>Sure I am, that the Lord will avenge the Poor, and maintain the cauſe of the helpleſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus in ſhort having given you a Traditional account of the time and manner of the diſcovery of the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinalneſs of this Water; I am now by my Method engaged to give my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of what Minerals it conſiſts of, and to ennumerate the ſeveral Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes they are approvedly found good
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57358:54"/>for, and ſuccesfully uſed againſt; offering ſuch Reaſons therefore, as are fairly deducible from the Natural Energie of the ſaid Minerals.</p>
               <p>The Obſervation and Experience which I have hitherto made from the <hi>Corporal ſubſtances,</hi> which I have found by <hi>Evaporation, Sublimation, Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation</hi> &amp;c. induced me to judge this <hi>Water</hi> principally to conſiſt of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Salt, Alum,</hi> and ſome <hi>Sulphur</hi> (for there not having been, as yet, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny digging, nothing can be collected that way; though an expert Artiſt aſſiſted with a good Purſe might much dilucidate and further this Diſcovery) and by tracing the known experience of its effects, I have found them to be ſuch as aptly, and ſuitably agree with the nature of theſe Minerals; For though I do not altogether diſſent from <hi>Galen</hi> who judged the quality of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be rather diſcoverable by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> than <hi>Reaſon;</hi> (ſo making them <hi>Remedium Empiricum</hi>) yet I ſhall not handle theſe waters ſo <hi>Empirical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as altogther to exclude <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57358:54"/>ſhall endeavor to diſcover the genuine and proper cauſes of its effects, which <hi>experience</hi> hath already found out.</p>
               <p>The <hi>ſenſible operation</hi> of this <hi>VVa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is moſtly by <hi>Seige,</hi> whereby ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are as effectually purged, as if they had taken a ſtrong <hi>Cathartick Potion,</hi> ſometimes by <hi>vomit,</hi> and more ſeldom by <hi>Sweat,</hi> and ſometimes by <hi>all three wayes</hi> of evacuation the Property of it, being to vary its operation according to thematter it meets with in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Bodies into which it is taken. The cauſe of the Purgative quality of it, is not (as many vainly and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly affirm) <hi>ravione ponderis,</hi> by reaſon of the great quantity of it being drunk; for ſo any water may purge: but it is by reaſon of ſon its <hi>Nitrous Salt,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with it is infected, which ſtimulat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the expulſive faculty of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach and guts, provokes to <hi>Stoole:</hi> And the reaſon of its operating by <hi>vomit,</hi> may be attributed to the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the ſtomach, and the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Nature to help it ſelf that way: &amp; that it ſhould ſometimes move <hi>ſweat</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:57358:55"/>is no marvail, ſince all <hi>Niters</hi> are na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally apt to do ſo.</p>
               <p>The Enumeration of this waters Specifick vertues you may take in this Catalogue of Diſeaſes, for which dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience findes it effectual: It effectually opens, and reſerates all obſtructions in the Inteſtines where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever latent, eſpecially thoſe of the <hi>Liver, Spleen, Meſaraick veines, Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ereas,</hi> the <hi>Biliary <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>terine</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinary Paſſages,</hi> by which means ſuch long, lingring, and almoſt incurable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers are bred, as the <hi>Schirrus Hepatis &amp; Lienis,</hi> the hard Tumours of the Liver, and Spleen, the <hi>Flatus Hypochondriacus,</hi> the Black and Yellow Jaundice, the Cholick, the ſtone and gravel in the Kidney and Bladder, all obſtruction, difficulties, and ſharpneſs of Urine, the <hi>Haemorrhoides, Chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick paſſion, Tenaſmus, Cachexia, Scurvy,</hi> the <hi>Dropſie, Chloroſis</hi> or <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſickneſs,</hi> ſtoppage of the Terms, <hi>Suffocatio uteri,</hi> Fits of the Mother, and many ſuch like Diſtempers (which being the unavoidable Conſequents of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57358:55"/>the Obſtructions of the ſaid noble <hi>viſcera</hi>) may by the due and proper uſe of <hi>this water,</hi> find an admirable and approved Remedy: for there is not one of the Diſtempers above enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merated, upon which in my ſhort time (<hi>viz.</hi> within two years laſt paſt) I have not had the opportunity to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment its effects, whereupon I af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that if properly, and with due caution it be uſed, it is an abſolute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, for the more ſlight, and hugely inſtrumental towards the eradicating of the moſt ſtubborn of them.</p>
               <p>Now the Reaſon why it ſhould be ſo very excellent in all theſe forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Diſtempers, is (1) From the cleanſing, and attenuating quality of the <hi>Nitrous Sal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> (2) From the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringent and cooling faculty of the <hi>Alum,</hi> and (3ly.) From the healing and the detergent property of the <hi>Sulphur:</hi> And to every one of theſe Concrete Juices ſeverally, ſince Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians do attribute the faculty of open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Obſtructions of the Liver, Spleen, Meſaraicks &amp;c. how much
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57358:56"/>more efficacious for the reſerating all the ſaid obſtructed Paſſages, muſt this <hi>VVater</hi> needs be, which (<hi>Nature</hi> play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Chymiſt</hi>) hath impregnated with all their united qualities.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Femal Sex</hi> are more eſpecially beholding to this <hi>Fructifying water,</hi> there being no Medicinal <hi>water</hi> ever yet known in this Kingdom, that could juſtly pretend to foecundate the <hi>womb</hi> and cauſe Fruitfulneſs, like this: If ſterility be cauſed from the <hi>Coldneſs</hi> and <hi>Moiſture</hi> of the Womb; here is the heating and drying quality of <hi>Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur</hi> to rid the <hi>Matrix</hi> of its frigidity, and Super fluous humidity, that made it <hi>intenacious,</hi> whereby it is made capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of <hi>Conception:</hi> If from an <hi>hot and dry</hi> Conſtitution of the womb, the ſpirit of the <hi>Sperm</hi> be diſſipated, and become exhauſted of its <hi>Spermatick</hi> vertue, here is the Cooling and attenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating faculty of the <hi>Nitre,</hi> to moiſten and cool it, thereby making it a fit <hi>Receptacle</hi> for the <hi>virile</hi> Seed. If from its plenitude of groſs, clammy, and excrementitious humours, which is a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:57358:56"/>very frequent and ordinary cauſe of Barrenneſs (the Matrix, being, as it were, the <hi>Canalis,</hi> whereinto all the parts of the Body do diſcharge their Superfluities) here is the abſterging and cutting qualities of the <hi>Nitrous</hi> and <hi>Aluminous Salts,</hi> to cleanſe, divide and carry off all <hi>viſcoſity,</hi> and ſo to make way for <hi>Conception.</hi> In fine, this <hi>water</hi> is furniſhed with ſuch apt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications to take away ſterility, and cauſe fruitfulneſs, that it ſeems deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by nature, as an <hi>univerſal Remedy</hi> againſt <hi>Barrenneſs,</hi> from whatſoever cauſe it be, by vertue of the diverſe Mineral Impregnations, with which Nature by its powerful Ferments hath endued it.</p>
               <p>This water excellently extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all manner of <hi>inward inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> it ſweetens all <hi>ſharp humours,</hi> is good for <hi>ſalt diſtillations,</hi> admirably helps <hi>ſcalding urines</hi> (as is before hinted) and is approvedly beneficial for the <hi>Running of the Reines,</hi> whether <hi>ſimple,</hi> or <hi>virulem,</hi> and for other <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes,</hi> which have <hi>Analogy</hi> with theſe.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:57358:57"/>
               <p>This is the moſt abſolute and ſureſt Remedy for the <hi>Gout</hi> (as I have great Reaſon to believe) that is yet known, let the Body be but prepared before hand, and then properly uſed: For we muſt not expect (as I ſhall ſhew hereafter) that it can do any great feates of it ſelf alone, but aſſiſted by <hi>Art,</hi> in many caſes, (and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in <hi>this</hi>) it doth <hi>wonders.</hi> Nature and Art muſt ſerve each others <hi>turnes,</hi> as the Poet intimates.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Praevenit humanum Stabilis</hi> Natura <hi>laborem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Servit Naturae legibus</hi> Artis <hi>opus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Nature mans labour often doth prevent,</l>
                  <l>And Art again doth ſerve Natures intent.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The real experiments (which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are able to teſtify they have made in this caſe <hi>viz.</hi> of the <hi>Gout</hi>) ſeriouſly commends the uſe of it, to all that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour under the tyranny of that mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and implacable Diſtemper. And the Reaſon hereof, I take to be from the <hi>Nitre,</hi> (which in this <hi>Water</hi> I hold
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57358:57"/>to be <hi>ex Praedominio</hi>) which by <hi>quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> the vaporous humours, that are too much in motion, and by <hi>fixing</hi> the ſharp <hi>Volatile Spirit,</hi> that is in the <hi>Blood,</hi> doth prove ſo excellently ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual for <hi>preſent</hi> eaſe, and <hi>future</hi> prevention.</p>
               <p>Very excellert muſt alſo this <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> be againſt all ſorts of Worms in your Bodies, ſince each of thoſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Minerals</hi> (with which it is tinged) is commonly known to deſtroy them of it ſelf alone; therefore much more effectual muſt <hi>this water</hi> needs be (which <hi>Nature,</hi> being the Art (as I may ſo ſay) of the Almighty, hath ſo Artificially compounded) in utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroying thoſe pernicious <hi>Vermin,</hi> which cauſe ſo many various Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and frightful Symptoms in old and young; And that it is ſo very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in this caſe I have had ſufficient experience.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Water</hi> corroborates the Brain and Nerves, and ſo prevents or cures the Apoplexy, Falling Sickneſs, Palſy, Dizzineſs, Ach of the Head, andall
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:57358:58"/>ſuch like Symptoms; (ſo that it be not taken actually cold, as I ſhall ſhew hereafter;) It ſtrengthens the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, cauſeth good digeſtion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes Crudities, it maketh groſs and fat Bodies lean, and the lean fleſhy; In a word, <hi>this water</hi> will effect whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever by any intention in a Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal way is to be performed by open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Obſtructions, evacuating ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humours, allaying Vapours, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Blood, and corroborating all the parts of the Body.</p>
               <p>There is a <hi>Corporal Subſtance</hi> which I extract from <hi>this water,</hi> of which after ſerious and diligent Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I have with admirable ſucceſs made uſe for the Cure of <hi>Intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Feavers,</hi> which (I may with great truth averr) doth more infallibly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Intention, than the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Cortex Indicus,</hi> or <hi>Jeſuits Powder;</hi> For out of 125 Experiments upon old and young, which I have made with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in 19 Months laſt paſt, there was not above 4 that failed to anſwer the deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red effects: It hath not only allayed
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57358:58"/>the fury of the preſent, or next ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>Paroxiſm,</hi> but hath totally e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected that <hi>unwelcome gueſt,</hi> that <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical Intruder,</hi> viz. the <hi>Ague,</hi> which it performes (as I take it) by depreſſing the power of the <hi>Morbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fick,</hi> and by advancing of the <hi>Natural ferment,</hi> and by ſupplying the defects of the <hi>Blood,</hi> by communicating that to it, which is by Nature conſimilar to its own preſervative Salt. I know the proceſs of this extract the Reader will here expect; but I have ſome private Reaſon, that, at preſent forbids it; not that I envy the world the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of knowing it, <hi>there is a time for all things, and a ſeaſon for every pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe under the Sun.</hi> And when by a longer time and further opportunity I have collected a juſt amaſsment of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, ſo firmly grounded that they will endure the <hi>teſt</hi> of the <hi>Spagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick Criticks,</hi> and the Candid enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment the World ſhall give this Treatiſe, ſhall induce me to publiſh them alſo, then it is probable I may therewith pleaſure you with this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57358:59"/>and in the Interim be content with what I have offered, and know that I reſpect the <hi>Publick good</hi> before any private Intereſt whatſoever.</p>
               <p>This water outwardly uſed is very good for moſt Cutaneous Diſtempers, as Leproſy, Itch, Scabbs, Pimples, Ring-worms, Scurvy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It alſo diſſolves tumoures, and cureth old Ulcers, if the Parties ill-affected be waſht, or bathed therewith: or if the Curd made by boyling Milk therewith, be applied; And I am perſwaded, it being uſed by way of a warm Bath, it would be of great efficacy to conſume Hydropical tumoures, to eaſe or Cure Gouty, and Rheumatick dolours, and far more effectual alſo in the above ſaid Cutaneous Diſtempers; I have not as yet made any Experiment of it this way, but ſhall not omit the firſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient opportunity, becauſe it appears to me highly rational.</p>
               <p>Thus have I enumerated the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Diſeaſes, for which the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of many hath found <hi>this water</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual: But for the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of its effects
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:57358:59"/>which are ſo various, I have adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to give you a ſhort hint of my own Conceptions, only drawn from ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, as the time of mine acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance therewith, and fitting opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity hath offered to make; and ſhall take the boldneſs to engage, (if time and opportunity ſhall by real experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and from concluſions rationally deduced from thence, furniſh me with grounds for any different Reaſons) to endeavour to ſuperſtruct a more conſiſtent <hi>Fabrick:</hi> For <hi>Day unto Day uttereth ſpeech, Night unto Night ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth knowledge,</hi> (Pſal 19.2.) <hi>This Day may be the</hi> Diſciple of <hi>To morrow;</hi> and <hi>To morrow</hi> of the <hi>next</hi> following; therefore I ſhall not be ſo poſitive, as peremptorily to commend my preſent Opinion, leſt Time (Truths Touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone) ſhould ſupply me with a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. For it is here, as it is with the Art of Phyſick in general; The chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of the two Leggs it goes upon, is experience: and I muſt confeſs, that it is in this caſe a ſurer way of arguing
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:57358:60"/>from the Effect to the cauſe, than <hi>è<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>contra.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Per varios caſus Artem experientia fecit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exemplo monſtrante viam,</hi> &amp;c.—</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>The Art of Phyſick by experience came,</l>
                  <l>Without Examples guide it had been lame.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But though Experience was the firſt in order, and ought in this caſe to march in the Front, yet effectually to make good the Fight againſt the ſtrong and numerous Army of our innate Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, (which are dayly drawing up their Forces to ſtorm our frail and decaying <hi>Tabernacles</hi>) we muſt upon neceſſity make Reaſon the <hi>Rereward:</hi> leſt truſting to much to <hi>Empirical aid,</hi> we too ſadly experiment our folly, and irrecoverably become <hi>Captives</hi> to our mercileſs Diſeaſes; and ſo I will paſs to the <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:57358:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>(SECT. V.)</hi> Of the time and manner of drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Water, with the Dyet to be obſerved, and Exerciſe to be uſed in drinking of it.</head>
               <p>THE Time for drinking this wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, is to be underſtood either in reference to the Seaſon of the Year, or to the time of the day. As to the Seaſon of the Year, I prefer neither Summer, nor Winter, Spring nor Fall, but as Occaſions, and every Ones particular Circumſtances ſhall require, but in general, whenſoever the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is clear, and dry, then the <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is beſt, as well in Winter, as in Summer; yea, in hard froſty weather, the water is commonly ſtrongeſt, by reaſon of the Air's Antiperiſtaſis, keeping its Mineral Spirits from eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porating away; and then it is of more quick, and ſpeedy paſſage than in the midſt of Summer, when the Air by heat is adapted to draw unto it ſelf,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:57358:61"/>and deprive it of its volatile Spirits. And therefore ſince heat is ſo apt to attract thoſe ſpirits, the fitteſt time of the Day (more eſpecially in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer) to drink it, is any time between Sun-riſing, and till it be an hour high, or therebouts, and ſo you will be ſure to receive it in its ſtrength; and to take it oftner, than once a day, I hold very injurious to Nature, and prejudicial to moſt Conſtitutions. But as to the drinking of it cold, which is the general cuſtom, I confeſs, I cannot but declare my Diſlike, unleſs to ſtrong and very robuſt Bodies. For the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach being a Nervous part, is eaſily offended by that which is actually cold, and is thereby impedited from exerciſing its functions aright, by which errour many muſt needs be the ill Conſequences, the Defect of the firſt not being to be made good by the other Concoctions. Cold deſtroying the faculties of the Stomach, (which are maintained by heat) breeds therein many crudities, whereby Gouts, Dropſies, Rheums,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:57358:61"/>Coughs, Colicks &amp;c. muſt needs be produced. To drink it <hi>cold</hi> alſo I hold it mightily inimical to all perſons, that have, or that are inclinable to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poplexy, Epilepſie, Palſie, Lethargy, Convulſions, Tremblings, &amp;c. For any thing actually <hi>cold,</hi> paſſing down the Throat muſt needs affect the Brain, the innermoſt Coat of the Jawes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing common with the Membranes of the Brain, the cold taken in, thereby is eaſily communicated to them, which thing is confirmed by <hi>Hippocrates</hi> (Aphor. Sect. 5.18.) <hi>Frigidum ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micum oſſibus, cleatibus, Nervis, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro, Dorſali Medullae; Calidum verò amicum. i. e.</hi> To drink water cold is hurtful to the Bones, Teeth, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news, Brain, Marrow of the back, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but <hi>warm</hi> is good, and profitable: Not to inſiſt any longer upon this matter, I take it to be the ſafeſt courſe in all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to take this Water warm, ſince o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther waies it cannot rationally be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed ſo eaſily to paſs through the ſmall Meanders of the Body: we by familiar uſe do dayly ſee that <hi>warm</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:57358:62"/>water externally uſed, will deterge and ſcour off thoſe filthy adheſions, which water actually cold cannot; and what hinders the like preeminent ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects in our Bodies? It certainly inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates it felt the better through the ſmalleſt paſſages, and more powerful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſſolves the Coherence of ſuch clammy, tough, and ſticking ſubſtances, (which like Glew adhere to the walls of the Stomach and Coats of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtines) preparing them and making them the fitter for expulſion by Seige. It alſo paſſes the ſooner to the Reins, and cleanſing them by its abſterſive quality, it carries along with it through the Vrinary Paſſages, whatſoever lyes lurking there, as a fit matter to cauſe Obſtructions, and doth the better qualify that heat, which is ſo efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous towards the Coagulation of <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> and Generation of the <hi>Stone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But in adviſing to drink this <hi>Water warm,</hi> I do not mean, that it is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and abſolutely inconvenient for all Perſons whatſoever to drink it cold, for they whoſe Conſtitutions are
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57358:62"/>ſtrong, whoſe <hi>Ventricle</hi> and <hi>Viſcera</hi> are firm and robuſt, (thereby being the better enabled to undergo the greate exerciſe,) may queſtionleſs with benefit drink it cold; But for thoſe of weak Conſtitutions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is better and ſafer to drink it warm, ſo that it be done with as little loſs of its Spirits, as may be. For as <hi>this</hi> wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth conſiſt of preceptible Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Vapours, ſo doth it alſo of ſubtle and inſenſible Spirits, or Atomes, and <hi>theſe</hi> by a ſmall heat will eaſily eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, and take their flight into the open Air, though the other by heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or boyling, will not budge, which is collective from common experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; for if Beer be made of this (as of ordinary water) it is commonly known to operate effectually by ſtool, which is occaſioned by a <hi>fixt Salt</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed therein (remaining after ebulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) which excites the expulſive fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of the Guts; For this kind of Salt cannot be evaporated by the ſtrongeſt Fire, but is the laſt ſubſtance that remains therein, being <hi>incombuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:57358:63"/>and <hi>inevaporable;</hi>) So that in ſome caſes you may make Poſſet-drink of it with Milk (which the Poor People which conſtantly attend at the Wells will eaſily procure you) after the uſual way: But in other caſes were it is not ſafe to drink it cold, and yet requiſite to retain as much of the above-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>ſubtle</hi> ſpirits as may be, I take it to be the beſt way to get ſome Milk (which the Poor People that conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attend at the <hi>Wells,</hi> will eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure you) and to 3 Pints of Water, put about a quarter of a Pint of Scald<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hot, or Boyling Milk, whereby it will become of a convenient warmth to be drank, and ſo you may propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Milk to what quantity of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you pleaſe; But I inſtance in that quantity, becauſe for a Body of mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle Age, and competent ſtrength, I hold it a fit proportion to begin with; and ſo increaſing every day gradually till he riſes, to 8, or 9 Pints more, or leſs, as he ſhall be able to bear it: and ſo again to decreaſe by degrees, end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where he began: As ſuppoſe ſuch
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:57358:63"/>a perſon ſhould deſign to allott him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf 20 days to drink the water, and the firſt day he ſhould begin with 3 pints; then to <hi>that proportion</hi> I would have him add half a pint daily for the next ſix days, 3 quarters of a pint for the eighth day, almoſt a pint for the ninth day, and a whole pint for the tenth day, (which being your great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Riſe</hi> will amount to eight pints and an half) and ſo for the remaining ten days daily to drink the ſame propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions backwards, as what quantity you drank the tenth day, you are to drink the eleventh, and what propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you drank the ninth day, you are to take the twelfth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which brings you to the ſame Proportion for the twentieth and laſt day, with which you began the firſt day.</p>
               <p>But the juſt and convenient quantity of water to be taken at one time, is a thing that cannot poſſibly be juſtly aſcertained in regard of the ſeveral Differences of Age, Sex, Strength, and other manifold Circumſtances; yet generally they reap the greateſt bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:57358:64"/>by it, that can drink moſt and throughly concoct it.</p>
               <p>And ſince by drinking the water too faſt, by allotting too ſhort a time for taking the full proportion, divers ſymptoms are cauſed, (through the over-charging, and compreſſing the Veſſels) as Gripings, Cold Sweats, Tenſions, Giddineſs in the head, and the like: I would adviſe to take at firſt a third part of the proportion, and then exerciſe half an hour, then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther third part, and exerciſe the ſame time, and then the laſt, or remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part, with exerciſe till all be paſt out of the Body, or till Dinner-time.</p>
               <p>It is good <hi>before</hi> the taking of the Water to excite the Natural heat by walking (yet not as to Sweat) for thereby the water will find the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and better paſſage: Whilſt the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>is taking,</hi> the propereſt exerciſe to be uſed is alſo <hi>Walking,</hi> or bowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, pitching of the Barr, or leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ſtrength ſhall permit, ſo they be uſed moderately. And when <hi>all the Proportion</hi> of Water is in the Body;
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57358:64"/>the like exerciſe is neceſſary alſo for the better digeſtion thereof, by ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up the Natural heat, whereby the internal Veſſels being heated, the water will be more forcibly attract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and excited for expulſion, but a great care ought to be taken that the exerciſe be not ſo violent as to provoke Sweat, for thereby many inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences may accrue: And that you ſleep not, till it is digeſted, and wrought off: ſtanding ſtill in the Sun, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the ground are very injurous and hurtful.</p>
               <p>For thoſe that have the convenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Coach, or Horſe, it will not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs for ſuch to alight about a mile be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they come unto the Wells, and walk it thither, and ſo exerciſing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter every proportion of <hi>Water,</hi> the <hi>time</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> before mentioned; and when they have taken the whole proportion for that time, they may walk homewards about a Mile, or bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and then take Coach, or Horſe agen. For when by thus walking, the Paſſages of the Body are, by the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:57358:65"/>excitation of the Natural heat, laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Riding in Coach, or on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back by compreſſing the Muſcles of the Abdomen, will very much further its operation.</p>
               <p>After every Draught or two of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it may be convenient, to take a few Carroway-Comfits, Coriander-Seed prepared, Elicampane, or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelico preſerved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to help the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of the Water, to promote its paſſage, and to comfort all the Veſſels through which the water paſſes.</p>
               <p>And above all, temperance in reſpect of <hi>Diet</hi> is to be obſerved all the time of drinking it; The <hi>Italian</hi> Proverb is to be taken notice of, <hi>viz. He that will eat much, muſt eat little:</hi> Meat for the moſt part offends more by its <hi>Quantity</hi> than <hi>Quality:</hi> a ſober <hi>Dyet</hi> as it prevents many Infirmities, ſo it is able to cure many Diſeaſes by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing the Crudities, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperance hath bred already, and to reduce all the humours of the Body to its true Natural temperature. And on the other ſide, <hi>Exceſs</hi> in <hi>Diet</hi> to
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57358:65"/>take in more meat and drink, than Nature requires, or can digeſt, by hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the Concoction of the Chyle, doth cauſe it to paſs crude through the whole Body; from whence of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, great Obſtructions, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Hypochondriacal diſtempers are cauſed.</p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Quality</hi> of Meat, let ſuch be uſed as may not hinder the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of the water, ſuch as be of good nouriſhment, of eaſie digeſtion, and may freely paſs through the veſſels, which ſerve for its diſtribution. In more particular manner, all ſalt meats, Ducks, Geeſe, Bacon, Tripes, all ſalt Fiſh, Eeles, old Cheeſe, Leeks, Oni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Cabbage, Muskmillions, Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are to be avoided; And good young ſucculent Beef, Mutton, Lamb, Veal, Chickens, Pullets, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keys, Partridges, Pheſants, young Conies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are to be uſed. Alſo Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Pears, Plums, Cherries, ripe Gooſeberries, Raſp-berries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are allowable, if ſparingly eaten, and that a little before ſupper, and then they
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:57358:66"/>help to temper the Blood.</p>
               <p>As for Drinks, I commend Beer or Ale, that is neither too ſtale, nor too ſmall: I approve alſo, that thoſe whoſe Stomachs are uſed thereunto, may uſe <hi>Spaniſh, French,</hi> or <hi>Rheniſh</hi> Wines, ſince it may prove of very ill conſequence to thwart and croſs Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome all on a ſudden. But I am of an Opinion that the cuſtome of drinking ſo much white and Rheniſh wines at meals, occaſions multitudes of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers, becauſe they being Diure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall, and very penetrative, do carry down with them the raw and crude juice of the meate to the Liver before it be concocted.</p>
               <p>Let the <hi>Supper</hi> be larger than the <hi>Dinner,</hi> 6 or 7 hours after it, becauſe by Supper-time the Stomach will be leſs relax, and be more capacitated to concoct a greater quantity of Meat.</p>
               <p>After the ending of the waters it will be neceſſary for a month or ſix weeks, to uſe a very ſpare Diet to keep out, and prevent all Crudities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:57358:66"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>(SECT. VI.)</hi> Of the Neceſſity of the learned, and skillfull Phyſician's Advice, both before, at, and after the taking of the Waters.</head>
               <p>THough this Water proceeds from ſuch Minerals, as make it highly convenient, and proper for the ſeveral Diſeaſes above-mentioned: Yet we are not to imagine it ſuch an abſolute Remedy, as that of it ſelf it is able to cure Diſeaſes without any rule for the uſe of it, or without any other helps to be ſometimes joined with it. But it is neceſſary, that the learned and skilful Phyſician (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch an One as is well acquainted with the water) ſhould be adviſed with, both <hi>before, at,</hi> and <hi>after</hi> the taking the water.</p>
               <p>Firſt, before you take it, as you love your life and health, be adviſed what Preparations are requiſite to prevent the great inconveniences,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:57358:67"/>which otherwaies may fall out: For if you ſhould take this water upon a foul Stomach into a Body replete with groſs humours, it (by carrying them with it, with a ſpeedy impetuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, into the veins, which, being not capacious enough for the reception of ſuch a quantity of collected matter, do become thereby obſtructed) inſtead of doing good, and reſerating Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, doth, for want of due pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, wedge thoſe groſs humours into the veins, which give riſe to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtubborn Diſeaſes, before perhaps altogether unknown to the Patient: and upon this account it is that many (either receiving no benefit, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps no ſmall dammage by this Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) are apt to complain of it, and thereupon do dehort others from the uſe of it, and ſo ungratefully blaſpheme the great bleſſing of God beſtowed upon theſe Wells.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Whilſt you are taking it, the Phyſicians advice is alſo neceſſary, by reaſon of the unexpected ſucceſs, and unlookt for appearing of Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57358:67"/>which may fall out. As if upon taking of it, it paſs not freely through the body, but is accidentally retained; it is to be conſidered in what part of the body it is at a ſtand, that it may be evacuated by ſome appropriated means: for if it be retained in the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or Hypochondries (which will be apparent by wind rumbling up and down, and oppreſſure) a Clyſter is convenient for its evacuation: if in the Stomach (which will appear by a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to vomit) ſome opening and cleanſing Cathartick will be conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to make a free paſſage for it from thence. If it be retained in the habit of the body, (which is evident by a heavineſs, and chillneſs over the body without the aforeſaid rumbling wind, and oppreſſure) ſome Hydragogall Medicines will be neceſſary. So that as, upon the aforeſaid Account, the Phyſicians advice is neceſſary to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite the water to a quicker paſſage; So, in other caſes, he may have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to hebetate, and ſtop its too active operation, or may find it neceſſary
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:57358:68"/>to rectify ſome other emergent ill Symptoms, or perhaps to adviſe you to deſiſt for a time from drinking it, or it may be, he may hold it requiſite to uſe with the water ſome <hi>Cathartick, Diuretick</hi> or <hi>Deoppillative</hi> Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, appropriated to the Diſtemper for which it is drunk; So that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the variety of particular Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, which may happen, and the various Circumſtances incident in ſo many ſeveral caſes, it being impoſſible for any one to intimate particular <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections,</hi> without dangerous miſtakes to the Patient, I muſt referr you (as properly appertaining) to your skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Phyſician.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, and laſtly, the Phyſicians Counſel, and help is as neceſſary, when you have finiſht your <hi>Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinking</hi> Courſe; for directing you, how to carry off the terrene Sediments and crude ſeroſities, which the water muſt needs have left behind it in your Bodies: which would elſe be carried down into the ſmaller Veſſels and cauſe obſtructions, whereby many great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:57358:68"/>and Symptoms may fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; which if by a right courſe carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off, will perfect the Cure, which the water perhaps hath but happily begun, and made preparation for; but of theſe things I can ſay nothing, but in general terms, and therefore muſt (as before) commend you to your Phyſician for more full, and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Inſtructions, as occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire.</p>
               <p>Since the diſpoſing hand of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath ſettled me in <hi>Lewiſham,</hi> the place which God, out of his libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral bounty hath bleſt with this <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinal water,</hi> and there freely diſpenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it; I look upon it as a <hi>Providential intimation</hi> to oblige <hi>me</hi> not only to uſe <hi>my</hi> utmoſt endeavour to inveſtigate its vertues for the general good, but alſo <hi>freely</hi> to afford <hi>my advice</hi> for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of ſuch that intending to drink this water ſhall deſire it.</p>
               <p>So that I ſhall take leave to give no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice that if any Perſons ſhall be pleaſed to conferr with <hi>me,</hi> about taking this water, if I am not at the <hi>Wells,</hi> I ſhall
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:57358:69"/>be God willing ready at <hi>my houſe</hi> eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day (till 10 a Clock in the Morning, if no more than ordinary occaſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervene) to afford <hi>my</hi> beſt <hi>Advice gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> where alſo (if there ſhall be found occaſion) they may be ſupplied (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any further trouble) with variety of <hi>Medicinal preparations,</hi> appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſeveral <hi>Diſtempers,</hi> this <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is to be uſed for.</p>
               <p>For I am not aſhamed to confeſs that I have met with ſome Diſeaſes ſo inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terately fixt, ſo ſtubborn and difficult to be eradicated, that all that I could do by the uſe of <hi>Artificial</hi> Medicines have proved ſucceſleſs, till being aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>this</hi> (of Natures own prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring) and then in no very long time have they given place, and been quel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. So that I think it no diſcredit to fight at all lawful Weapons againſt ſuch inveterate and implacable ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57358:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
